Codey: Hello, farmers, and welcome to another episode of The Harvest Season.
Codey: My name is Cody.
Chelsea: And my name is Chelsea.
Codey: And we are here today to talk about cottage core games.
Codey: Woo, but mostly bugs, mostly bugs.
Chelsea: Woo!
Chelsea: Mostly.
Codey: Um, I have a confession to make.
Codey: Every single time I read this intro.
Codey: My brain is like, you're going to say the other person's name.
Codey: Like, I'm going to say, my name is Chelsea, and it's like,
Chelsea: I'm just thinking that. I'm like, 0 no, I'm not Cody.
Chelsea: I not Cody.
Chelsea: I am not Cody.
Codey: I guess it's just a blank, like he has just left a blank spot, and I'm like, I start getting to that, that part of the line, and I'm like, what is my name?
Chelsea: Who am I?
Codey: Who am I?
Codey: Okay, this today we are going to finish up bug month.
Codey: So, um, the game that we will be tangentially, or um, not tangentially, that we will be uh, obligated to talk about at the end so that this can remain a game-based podcast, uh, is B simulator.
Codey: Both Chelsea and I played that game.
Chelsea: Yep.
Codey: Um, But before that, of course, is Cody's Entomology Corner, where I will bombard y'all with the fire hose of information that is my knowledge of bugs.
Codey: Um, and there's a lot of it.
Codey: But I have tried to hold myself back.
Chelsea: Don't hold yourself back.
Codey: I know, it's just so hard because we're discussing what is known as the big 4, the big 4 orders, like the most where the most of the diversity is, and I just I have so much I want to talk about.
Codey: And honestly, if I went through and talked about every single family that I want to talk about or every single antidote.
Codey: It would be like a 20 hour podcast.
Codey: So I had to like really slim it down.
Codey: Um, But yeah, it's there.
Codey: But before I rant.
Codey: Um, we, there is no news because this is again just like kind of our off week, uh, or off month or whatever.
Codey: Um, the episodes following this one, I believe, is going to be like the news catch up episodes.
Codey: So it's going to be a lot of news therein.
Codey: Um, but since there's no news.
Codey: Uh, We'll just gab about kind of what's going on in our life.
Codey: So, uh, Chelsea, what are you, what's, what's been going on?
Codey: Like, have you done anything fun?
Codey: read anything, played anything?
Chelsea: Um, so I've been getting back into neopets.
Codey: Yeah, yeah.
Chelsea: We don't have time to get into that.
Chelsea: We don't have time for that.
Chelsea: Um.
Codey: Okay, just, I mean, we could probably have a podcast episode about it.
Codey: But, like, do you take us through like how much do you plan a day?
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: Do you just like do a day, do your dailies or are you checking a couple times a day or what?
Chelsea: Yeah, so.
Chelsea: Like once or twice a day.
Chelsea: So, um, I tried to get my old account back, but I know that there was an underscore somewhere and I can't remember where the underscore it was. So they tried, they tried to recover it for me, but they couldn't, but like, God bless them for trying.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: I was like, moon beams with a Z underscore 76.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: They're like, oh, okay, maybe it's another underscore somewhere else.
Chelsea: I'm like, honestly, I'll just start fresh.
Chelsea: It's fine.
Chelsea: I bought one month of premium and it is unfair how different the game is when you have premium.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Hmm. Is the quality, but like the, it doesn't lag as much or?
Chelsea: To the point where I.
Chelsea: So there's no legging, there's no ads, there's no pop-ups.
Chelsea: You can use the super shop wizard instead of like.
Chelsea: Anyway, that's if you're into the game, but basically, it'll give you the cheapest option by default.
Chelsea: You get like the premium wheels, you get goody bags.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: It's like a daily
Chelsea: it's just, it's so unfair.
Chelsea: And I'd imagine if I was a kid, like, wow, why does this person have all of these things and I have to go to the soup kitchen?
Codey: I mean, honestly, I would still go to the soup kitchen and I would still play as a pauper and all of that if I could just not have lag.
Codey: So for the sake of the podcast and totally not to secure my own or to salvage my own curiosity or whatever.
Codey: How much is the premium?
Chelsea: Um, so it's $12.
Codey: That is not bad.
Chelsea: Um, and then the reason I got, honestly, the main reason I wanted it is because they have a function that's called, um, zap your pet.
Chelsea: So, You can take a regular pet and then you can zap it once every 365 days.
Chelsea: It can't just be like every time you start premium, they keep track of your year, um, and you can get like a really rare neoped.
Codey: Mm, mm, mm, mm.
Chelsea: So when I was a kid, I had a psi bunny, which you can't make anymore.
Chelsea: Um,
Codey: Really?
Chelsea: No, you can only get them on like their
Codey: Whoa.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: So I made one and then Kevin pointed out to me that I, I, I made this like throwaway pet, but I didn't change any of the personality features.
Chelsea: So now it says like, this money, well, assault from afar.
Chelsea: And you can't, you can't change it.
Codey: I do remember seeing that.
Chelsea: I'm like, no, she's really nice.
Chelsea: But no, so I really just wanted my side money.
Chelsea: Um, There's some that you still can't even use with the Zap machine, but it helps you not wait a whole year if there's one that you want that you can only create on their pet day.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Um, but we need to do a whole episode on your pets because I have so much to say about neopets.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, I, I really, my biggest thing with Neopetzel is the games.
Chelsea: Um.
Codey: Like I, like Destructo match, I could play that game forever.
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: But unfortunately, you can only send, quote unquote,
Codey: send your scores like 3 times a day, which is actually probably for the better because, um, I would just sit there playing that game all day.
Chelsea: Yeah, with.
Chelsea: Yep, and with premium, you can do it 4 times a day.
Codey: That extra one time is really a, is really a bit. I might have to try pre.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Maybe I'll try premium for a month, uh, and then we can cover it in a podcast episode and talk about it because because you you mentioned doing neopets again, and then I tried to play again, and I was like, y'all, I can't handle this lag.
Chelsea: That would be incredibly fun.
Codey: I can't handle these ads.
Codey: Like, the screen is just bombarded with ads and I would try and hit.
Codey: I would try and like click something, but an ad would pop up, like kind of near it and I would accidentally click the ad and I was just like, I can't, I can't do this.
Chelsea: No, it's an entirely different game without being like blasted with advertising.
Codey: Yeah, so I will probably.
Chelsea: Yeah, just for even one month, just try it and then we can do an episode.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Aside from that, um, went to a Lord Huron concert in July.
Chelsea: They were super fun to see outside.
Codey: Nice.
Chelsea: Uh, we have a big festival in Ottawa called Blues Fest, and um, it's never any blues artists, but that's how it started.
Chelsea: Uh, and usually the weather is terrible and it was perfect weather.
Chelsea: Lovely.
Chelsea: It was just great.
Chelsea: It was really nice to do that.
Codey: Yay.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: And then, um, I saw a Spider-Man brand new day, which I will not spoil, and my husband's a huge Spider-Man nerd.
Codey: Oh.
Chelsea: So that was fun.
Codey: But did you enjoy it?
Chelsea: I did, I did.
Codey: Is it? Okay.
Chelsea: It's yeah, it was a good time.
Codey: Nice.
Chelsea: But I will not spoil it yet.
Codey: Yeah, maybe give it a couple more, couple more weeks or something.
Codey: I don't know.
Chelsea: Mm-hmm.
Codey: I don't know if I'm caught up on Spider-Man movies.
Codey: Um, but I, so I think I need to, because I was talking to someone about which ones and they were like, oh, you're like one behind.
Codey: So I need to do that and then and then I can also watch, uh, brand new day.
Chelsea: Yeah, no, there's some tie-ins with the shows and I'm like, I don't have...
Codey: Ah.
Chelsea: I don't have time to do all of this research.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Like, I remember when the Avengers was like the pent ultimate.
Chelsea: Oh my god, all these people are combined.
Chelsea: This is great.
Chelsea: And then it turned into WandaVision. And like, which is fine.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: But then all these other shows that I just, I cannot.
Chelsea: And maybe I'm just like a casual fan.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Which I probably, yeah, I like I definitely a fake fan.
Codey: Fake.
Codey: Fake fan.
Chelsea: So I don't know the I don't know the whole the whole lore of it.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um, but, uh, It's not so bad in the movie to the point where you don't know what's happening.
Chelsea: So it's more stuff like, oh, I remember this Easter egg from the show or, oh, this tiny plotline is continuing from a previous show kind of thing.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, and some of it isn't even like necessarily that you won't understand.
Codey: It's just like, it is clear that there is something either from the way that the show is or the audience around you's reaction that like there is something else there that you're missing.
Codey: And I don't have the time.
Chelsea: I don't, but the thing, okay, so.
Chelsea: The episode, so last week's episode when you when you guys talked about being in the theatre and then approaching somebody, I love that for you because I had, no, I had a group of kids next to me and I have never in my life called another person out.
Codey: Uh-huh.
Chelsea: Like, I am such a patient person.
Chelsea: However, this group of 6 teenagers were put next to me to ruin my whole night because they asked when's Batman coming and they were being serious.
Chelsea: And so which is fine, whatever.
Chelsea: However, they were, like, one of them had their, their PSP out, like, full volume, full brightness, no shoes on, no socks on, throwing popcorn, like talking on the phone.
Codey: Dude.
Chelsea: And then so I was just like, are you done?
Chelsea: And they're like, guys.
Codey: I thought Canadians were supposed to be supposed to not do this.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: Right?
Chelsea: Um, so then, So I was like, are you done?
Chelsea: They're like done doing what?
Chelsea: And then the other teenager's like, listen, guys, we have to be friends.
Chelsea: We have to sit and experience this together for the next 2.5 hours.
Chelsea: So let's make sure we get along.
Chelsea: And I'm like just shut up.
Codey: Shut up.
Chelsea: Shut up.
Codey: Do you not hear?
Codey: Do you not see these kids?
Codey: These freaking kids.
Codey: Ugh
Chelsea: Anyway, so that, yeah, so I don't even remember what happened the 1st time.
Chelsea: So then the next day my kids really wanted to go.
Chelsea: So my Pat and I, we went alone the 1st night just to see how scary it would be, um, for my, for my youngest. And plus it just got us a date night.
Codey: Okay, yeah.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um, and then the next morning I was like, you know what?
Chelsea: I don't remember anything because all I remember is what these people next to me were talking about.
Chelsea: Um.
Codey: That's the thing is like they ruin it because then that's all you remember.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: And if you think about it again or like I know I'm going to have to rewatch the Odyssey just because there was that part in the movie.
Codey: And when I rewatch it too, I'll be like, I remember those people and it's going to ruin it again.
Chelsea: Yeah, exactly.
Codey: Like,
Chelsea: It wasn't even like they were excited about the movie.
Chelsea: They were just talking about other things had nothing to do with this.
Codey: No.
Chelsea: Anyway, so when I went the 2nd time with my children.
Chelsea: I actually remember, like understood what was happening.
Chelsea: And I actually remembered it, because I remember, uh, when I went with Pat.
Chelsea: I was like, I don't even remember this scene.
Chelsea: All I heard was this guy's PlayStation portable next to me.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Like, what are we doing?
Chelsea: Why are you paying all this money?
Chelsea: Because it's not cheap.
Chelsea: And then you're throwing your popcorn?
Codey: No.
Chelsea: What are we like, come on.
Codey: Some people's kids, man.
Chelsea: Not as bad as the Minecraft.
Chelsea: I don't know if you remember that people.
Codey: Oh no, what?
Chelsea: Check it.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Chelsea: Okay, some of the Minecraft movie came out.
Chelsea: There's this little scene where they go chicken jockey and then people would like throw their popcorn at the ceiling, scream and like throw each other around and there's videos of people like holding up real chicken.
Codey: Oh my God, in the theatre?
Chelsea: In the theatre. And then, like, every theatre, everywhere said, like, some theatres even paused it before and said, if anyone knows this, you were getting escorted out of the theatre.
Codey: Oh my goodness.
Chelsea: Oh my god, just look, I'm going to send you a video of like a chicken jockey compilation.
Codey: Yeah, I would love to see that.
Chelsea: Um, yeah, yeah, so. I don't know.
Chelsea: Maybe I'm maybe I'm just out of touch now because I'm old, but I never acted like that when I was a kid.
Codey: Maybe I'm out of touch, but I I had to, like, care for other people's experiences and respect for the world.
Chelsea: Yeah, I had consideration.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Yeah, exactly.
Codey: I feel that on a molecular level.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Well, I have been, uh, packing and just like getting ready to move because by the end of this month, uh, so we're recording this in August, um, you know, in, uh, we, we are out of this place uh, at the end of the month and I've lived in this house for 5 years.
Codey: So that is a lot of things, a lot of materials that have accrued objects that I now need to get rid of.
Codey: So I've been doing that, but I also had a bit some medical issues where I was kind of out of it for a couple of weeks.
Codey: And now I'm finally like at a place where I can do my work again.
Codey: And so I have like a good backlog of work to do.
Codey: before we leave this area.
Codey: I mean, I can still, there are certain things that I can still take.
Codey: Like, I have some specimens that are in ethanol that they all told, I mean, they're just in Ziploc bags.
Codey: They take not, they take like 2 grocery bags worth of space.
Codey: It's really not a big deal.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: But I have like, I'm looking around my room, maybe like 50 boxes of bugs.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: And these, the box, these boxes are like the size of a large textbook, if not bigger and each one has like a couple 100 bugs in it.
Codey: And so those I need to get rid.
Codey: I need to get rid of.
Codey: I need to, um, like give them, uh, I'm I'm currently labelling them and putting identifier numbers on them, and then they will be put into the mus- the entomological museum on my campus, but that is just a lot of time.
Chelsea: Mhm.
Codey: So I've been watching a lot of things.
Codey: So I watched, um, the newest season of Married at 1st Sight.
Codey: The American one.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: I watched today I watched Avengers, which is hilarious that you said Avengers, because I was like, I literally just watched that.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Um, I started rewatching Stephen Universe, um, which I don't really remember what happens in the end, like near the end seasons or whatever, but the 1st time that I started rewatching it and the theme song started, I like burst into tears.
Chelsea: Oh?
Codey: So there's some trauma.
Chelsea: Oh.
Chelsea: Life is so different from the last time you watched it.
Codey: No, it's just like, it's just that I remember all of the things that happen in, like, I remember at least that, like, the things that happen in the later seasons are like, ooh, like, there's, there's some, some heart.
Codey: Have you watched Stephen Universe?
Chelsea: No, because I've had so many people say, if you're not in a headspace,
Chelsea: Don't do it.
Codey: Yeah, there are a lot of themes, um, there that, yeah.
Codey: So, Um.
Chelsea: Is it on par with like bluey emotional damage?
Codey: It's like, it's a little further than that.
Codey: I mean, so you might, so Bluey might hit you harder as a parent, but Stephen Universe hits pretty hard too, like, I would say it's on par with, like, adventure time.
Chelsea: Oh no.
Codey: Where, yeah, where it comes off like at fear first.
Chelsea: Oh no, no, no, no.
Codey: Well, and because the person who started who, um, one of the people who made Adventure Time is the person who made Stephen Universe.
Codey: So, but it starts off as this cute little story and then like the longer it goes on, you're like, oh.
Chelsea: Yep.
Codey: Oh, no, no, like this is this is drama.
Chelsea: Oh, I'm questioning my existence now.
Codey: But I mean, I still really enjoy it.
Chelsea: No.
Codey: It's like, it's a really great story.
Codey: It's very heartwarming, but there is definitely there are definitely things.
Codey: But I will, I'm excited to, uh, rewatch it for sure.
Chelsea: That's good.
Codey: But uh, that is what we've been up to.
Codey: Woo.
Codey: Look, Al, we did it in about 15 minutes.
Codey: We're so...
Chelsea: Look at that.
Codey: We've got, we've, it's so much better than it has been in the past.
Chelsea: To be fair, we've been yapping for about half an hour before we hit record.
Codey: That's true.
Codey: So yeah, we did get a lot of that out of the way.
Codey: Okay, starting off my entomology corner.
Codey: Um, so you don't have a question necessarily, but you bring a question.
Codey: Do you want to tell the story of that?
Chelsea: Yeah, so I just asked when, my daughter, um, If you could ask anything about bugs.
Chelsea: What would you like to know?
Chelsea: And her question was, Cody, why do female ants not grow weight?
Codey: So I love this question because it shows that she already knows that worker ants, worker female ants don't have wings, but some but some ants do have wings.
Codey: So it like already shows that she already has had the curious mind to like watch ants and be like, what, like what is the, what's going on here?
Codey: Um, so I love that.
Codey: Thank you, Gwen, for the question.
Codey: Um, so, Ants have wings when they are reproductively active.
Codey: So when they are going to reproduce and like create a new colony.
Codey: Once they have mated, the males actually just die.
Codey: And but the females that have that used to have wings will drop those wings.
Codey: So they will basically, they flew, they made it, and then they'll find a place and then they'll, they'll, I don't, they chew off their wings.
Codey: I say we always say drop their wings, but they chew them off.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Um, and so she chews her wings out because she doesn't need them anymore. And there's not like nerves or anything, like she, I don't think she really feels it.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: She has a clutter free queen.
Codey: Yeah, she's like, I don't need.
Chelsea: She doesn't need those wings anymore.
Codey: don't need these anymore.
Codey: These are not going to serve me when I'm living in a tunnel.
Codey: Um, and so then she will begin a new colony.
Codey: She'll usually close off behind her and then she will spend uh, an amount of time, I think, like up to a week, of using her own reserves, like the, the, fat and and resources that she has reserved, like restored within her own body to create some workers and and hatch some workers raise them, et cetera, et cetera.
Codey: And then once, uh, and those will be uh, sorry, those workers will be non-winged.
Codey: So those are the ones you're going to see most often.
Chelsea: Interesting.
Codey: And those will be female.
Codey: It won't be until later in the year that the queen will stop producing workers and she'll start producing drones, which are the males.
Codey: Um, Yeah, so for the, for once she's founded a colony, she'll just make workers until it's like late, she gets some signal.
Chelsea: That is so cool.
Codey: Usually it's like photo period and temperature.
Codey: So how long the day the day is and the surrounding temperature and she'll basically can tell that it's becoming fall or whatever, they all have different times that they're active.
Codey: So, but she will then be like, okay, it's time to make males and then she'll switch to making males.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Codey: That's one, they either do that or they'll make males later in the, or make males first.
Codey: It really depends on the species.
Codey: But, um, the answer, I guess, short, long story short, is that female ants sometimes have wings, uh, but it is only the queens or the ones that are going that are going to be mated so that they can become queens.
Chelsea: Very cool.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Um, and that's,
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: Yeah, we tried to teach Gwen from the start.
Chelsea: Like all of our kids, instead of being fearful, be curious.
Chelsea: Because like you've said, it's like an innate thing that's passed down from parents, like, oh, bugs.
Codey: Yes.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Chelsea: If you just by nature, by default, kids are curious, they're not necessarily scared.
Chelsea: So that's why I have a photo of her holding her emotional support earthworm that she dug out of the yard.
Codey: Oh, my goodness.
Chelsea: that she brought she brought in the house once and she'd like, took care of it for a while.
Codey: I.
Codey: I love that.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Because that, I mean, that's also, I'll, I also was just talking to my husband about this recently that the best way to tell the, this, um, I'm saying, my brain thought the value of a person, but that's not true.
Codey: Like, the nature of a person, whether they are inherently good or inherently bad, whatever, is by how they treat or the life that cannot provide anything to them.
Codey: So, like, can't give them something.
Chelsea: Mm-hmm.
Codey: So yeah, watching someone, how do they interact with bugs?
Codey: How do they interact with dogs and cats?
Codey: And yeah, having that curiosity and respect for bugs.
Codey: I'm like, you're a good egg.
Codey: You're a good egg.
Chelsea: Yeah. I, I,
Codey: Well, and there was no doubt that you were going to raise some good eggs, so.
Chelsea: Oh thanks.
Codey: Just don't let her on neopets because that's that should stop with you.
Chelsea: Yeah, I'm breaking this generational curse.
Chelsea: It ends with me.
Codey: Generally, It probably also began with you based on our ages and the state of the internet.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: I did let she has one.
Chelsea: She made one neopet on my account.
Chelsea: Um, for our cat that passed away.
Chelsea: She's like, well, can we name a pet after? I'm like, yes, we can name one after our cat.
Codey: No.
Chelsea: So she likes to take care of that one and I let her pick the backgrounds and the paintbrushes and stuff for that one.
Chelsea: Um but yeah, no.
Codey: Sweet.
Codey: Well, thank you, Grand, for the question.
Codey: I feel like I rambled, uh, but that was, that's my answer.
Codey: Um, so next, I will do my uh, ramble about, um, insect diversity.
Codey: So last episode, we covered most of the hollow metabolis insects are the ones that have complete metamorphosis, except for what are considered the big 4 or called the big 4.
Codey: So these are the foremost speciose orders that contain the vast majority of described insect, and honestly just describe animal diversity, period.
Codey: Because insects are animals.
Codey: People, some people are like, no, they're not.
Codey: They are, they're animals.
Codey: They're not a separate thing.
Chelsea: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Um, and those 4 orders are Lepidoptera, which includes the butterflies and the moths, coleoptera, which is the Beatles, Diptera, which are the flies, and Hymanoptera, which includes the ants, the bees, and the wasps.
Codey: Um, which order is the most speciose order is a hotly debated topic. Um, I think currently, there are more described beetle species than any other thing, but the keyword there is described because there are likely so many undescribed insect species that we just don't have,
Codey: We don't haven't, like, even had the time, uh, or the knowledge or the, like the interest to identify these things.
Codey: Um, and so there are probably, I wrote 100s of 1000s of species still left to be identified, but then after I did some more research, like as I was writing my notes,
Codey: It's probably millions.
Codey: Um, yeah, so we, I think the estimate right now is that we've probably described maybe 30, 20 to 30% of what likely exists.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Um, which is nuts.
Codey: It's for insects, I mean, it's easier to have undescribed species because, you know, with mammals, it's like, well, yeah, we've probably seen all the mammals are huge, right?
Codey: But some of these things are so tiny.
Codey: Um, and you really have to take that time and that curiosity to stop and like look and look long enough to realise that it's it is a different thing from what has already been described.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: It could be a very similar thing, but something makes it different.
Codey: Yeah, and like it could.
Chelsea: You just don't have the time to figure out what that is.
Codey: Yeah, it could be, I mean, and there are some things, this is true of birds as well, where there's some birds that look very, very similar, but they have different, uh, different behaviours, different ecology.
Codey: There is something that has has separated them and they are no longer able to reproduce and produce viable offspring, which means that they are distinct species by the, what is known as the biological species concept.
Codey: Um, but there are, there's that in insects, like times, probably a 1000
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Right.
Codey: So yeah, there's still a lot to look at.
Codey: Um, so I pulled out 2 papers.
Codey: I just highlighted 2 papers in the show notes that folks can look at.
Codey: So there are some entomologists that think flies are the most diverse and the, the, article is titled uh, remarkable fly diversity in a patch of Costa Rican cloud forest, why inventory is a vital science.
Codey: So this paper gets at why we need to take the time to inventory things.
Codey: Um, And this actually, this Costa Rican cloud forest is where I went to Beatle school.
Codey: And one of the co-authors on this paper was one of the instructors at Beatle School. And he has, he has just found, it's not just flies.
Codey: Like he has also worked with other experts for other groups in this area. And just this one rather small geographic location.
Codey: Like they are just there just learning so much about, um, like diversity and speciation and finding things that are completely new, finding things that kind of fill gaps in what we already knew.
Codey: Um, It's wild.
Codey: It was really fun to go there too.
Chelsea: That's cool.
Codey: I recommend it.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: I recommend going to Costa Rica if people can.
Chelsea: Oh, that's exciting.
Chelsea: Yeah, go look at the bugs, of course.
Codey: Um, and the other thing, and there was just so many cool things.
Codey: there.
Codey: And then other people think that Hymenoptera will be the most specious order, um, because specific, because of um, parasitoid wasps.
Codey: So for most organisms that exist, there is a parasitoid of it.
Codey: So, and a lot of those parasitoids are wasps.
Codey: And by parasitoid, I mean, um, it is something that, uh, the, the adult herself does not consume, um, something, but she will lay an egg, and that egg will hatch, and then the larva will consume whatever the host is, be that a plant or another bug, um, or spiders or, you know, what it's, there's so many different things.
Chelsea: That's cool.
Codey: Um, and a lot of Paris toid uh, insects are within wasps.
Codey: So the, this, this journal, or journal, um, article title is just really funny to me.
Codey: quantifying the unquantifiable.
Codey: Why hymenoptera, not coleoptera, is the most specious animal order.
Chelsea: Aha.
Codey: They're throwing, that's some shade.
Codey: That's like, it's like you beetle people.
Codey: You're not the most music.
Chelsea: Not this, not that.
Codey: Um.
Chelsea: Beatle drama.
Codey: Beetle versus uh, wasp drama basically.
Codey: Um,
Codey: Yeah, and really, we'll, we'll know the answer in the long run when we finally start describing more of these things and having a greater understanding of them. So, um, so I will jump into the 1st order that I have chosen, which is Lepidoptera.
Codey: So again, these are the mods and butterflies.
Codey: Um, Lepidoptera means scale wing.
Codey: Lapido is scale.
Codey: Ptera is wing. And the majority of these organisms have a coil, what is known as a coiled proboscis.
Codey: So how they, the adults consume is they don't have like mandibles, they don't chew things, they lap them or suck them up through this appendage that is like a straw and it's called the proboscis.
Codey: Um, and the majority of Lepidopterans can actually coil their proboscis, but there are a couple, I think it's like 90% of them, but like 10% of them can't.
Codey: Um, And the other, like, really big factor of Lepidoptera is what is exactly what it says, the scaled wing.
Codey: So the wing itself is clear, but it is covered with all of these tiny, tiny scales that will make up, um, the image or the colouration that you see.
Codey: And a lot of the colouration that is on these is not a pigment.
Codey: So it's not that the scale itself is a certain colour.
Codey: It's a structural colouration.
Codey: So it has to do with the way that light waves actually bounce off of the scale will refract like the colour that you see.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Um, it's really, it's really interesting.
Chelsea: That's.
Codey: really scientific and lame.
Codey: I honestly don't understand structural colouration, but I just know that it's really cool because the majority of the time, um, colour is provided with pigmentation, but that's one of the reasons that butterflies are able to become so crazy colourful.
Chelsea: No.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Um, and not just butterflies, uh, like all Lebodopterans is because they have structural colouration instead.
Codey: Um, so the butterflies are within the super-order papilion.
Codey: Oh my gosh, Papilionidia.
Codey: Um, and the butterflies, you can tell a butterfly from a moth by the antennae.
Codey: So butterfly have clubbed antennae.
Codey: So at the end of their antenna.
Codey: They will have a little tiny club on it.
Codey: Um, I think there, I mean, there's, there are other things that can that can differentiate, but that's like a really easy one to see.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: There are 7 families of butterflies.
Codey: And, um, about 20,000 described species.
Codey: A couple of the families that I think are really cool include Papiliana Day, so this is the family that the super family is named after.
Codey: These are the swallow tails.
Codey: They are so named because of the quote unquote tales on some of them.
Codey: So when you're watching them fly.
Codey: They have these 2 parts of their wings that kind of jut out the back, just like a barn swallow or a tree swallow, violet green swallow.
Codey: Like all of these swallows like kind of have these like 2 pointed parts when they're flying.
Codey: Um, what I think is cool because I'm always, we're Pokemon nerds.
Codey: Um, caterpee is based off of a swallow tail caterpillar.
Codey: It's a specific it's the spice bush swallow tail, which actually spice bush is.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: a native plant to my region.
Codey: So I've been able to find these things like in the real.
Chelsea: That's exciting.
Codey: And there are, I mean, there are other swallow tail caterpillars kind of will look very similar, but, um, the spice, spice, 0 my goodness, spice, bush, swallow tail, is the one that like it 100% is based off of.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Um, Butterfree doesn't really look like an adult though.
Chelsea: I was gonna ask, is the, uh, is butter free, it look like the actual next stage?
Codey: Um, I no, not really.
Chelsea: Not really.
Chelsea: You mean it doesn't have a pink bow?
Codey: No.
Chelsea: Like the pink, like the pink butter free.
Codey: No, like the shiny one.
Codey: Um, The only thing, uh, that I'll say about this family is that the largest butterfly is within this, this family, so the largest butterfly in the world is the Queen Alexandra's Birdwing.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: It's uh, native to Papua, New Guinea, and it has an almost uh, one foot or 28 centimetre wingspan.
Chelsea: Oh my goodness.
Codey: Thick.
Chelsea: I was going to say, in my experience as an animal crossing player.
Codey: Yeah, yeah.
Chelsea: Because that's worth so much.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: No, yeah.
Codey: Yeah, Animal Crossing has a lot of butterflies in it.
Codey: Um, another butterfly family is Nymphaliday.
Codey: So these are the brush footed butterflies.
Codey: And many of the species within this family.
Codey: Their 1st pair of legs is modified into brushes, which I think are used for mating.
Codey: I don't know if we really know, or at least I don't really know.
Codey: It could also be for, like, feeding or something, it could be a species dependent.
Codey: Who knows?
Codey: Um, and this family includes the fritillaries, which are really pretty orange butterflies, and then also the monarch.
Codey: So, uh, the monarch of of migratory butterfly fame, where they're just an amazing example of long scale migration where they overwinter in Mexico, but then they disperse and into the breeding grounds up through North America.
Codey: Do you get them all the way up into Canada?
Chelsea: Uh, we did.
Codey: Oh, oh.
Chelsea: That sounds so depressing.
Chelsea: I've seen a few, not nearly as much as when I was younger.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: But they are.
Codey: They are also a great example of a success story where us, we realised that some of them were declining because of their lack of food and specifically the larval host plant.
Codey: So a lot of butterflies and moths don't have a specific thing that they go to necessarily as an adult.
Codey: It has to do with what their larvae eat.
Codey: So monarch, monarchs are so reliant on milkweed, which are plants in the genus Asclepias, flowers on the genius Asclepias.
Codey: And part of it, part of the reason why they have this type, like, um, co-evolved relationship is because the caterpillars will consume the, the milkweed, and there is a toxin that the milkweed secretes, that are cardentolides, but the monarch caterpillars will sequester these and basically use them.
Codey: It's like if you were to try, like the, the, The milkweed's like trying to rob a bank and it has a gun and the monarch caterpillar is like takes the gun and is like your, your move.
Chelsea: No, yeah.
Chelsea: Yeah, we have some milk weed in our yard.
Codey: Um,
Codey: Yeah, so that's, Yeah, so that's, the milkweed is a really good.
Chelsea: Uh, I try to keep it.
Codey: It's also just a very beneficial plant, uh, like not just for a larva host plant, but also just as a nectaring plant for other for other pollinators.
Codey: So it's just a good plant to have in general, but because of this need, the fact that the monarch is so closely tied to it, a lot of of milkweed has been planted across the United States, um, to try and provide like these stopping places for the monarchs because they need them like as they fly, um, north as well because the adults also really like nectar on it.
Codey: They'll nectar on other things, but they like it.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Did they get like drunk like bees do, like happy in the flower?
Codey: Uh, I don't think that they do necessarily, but the bees really, the bees do.
Chelsea: Take a whole bath in it.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, in some be, so some milkweed species, uh, are actually kind of sticky. Like, and so you might even, I've actually seen like honeybees that got stuck to the milkweed and died because they couldn't leave the flower, which is like, I think it has to do with the way that the milkweed disperses their pollen.
Chelsea: Oh no.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: They have these, like, capsules called pellenia and, um, they stick to the bee.
Codey: But if they, but if they like stick to the beat and also stick to the plant, you're kind of screwed.
Codey: But I don't know.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: I've just seen it a few times and been like, oof, that sucks, bud.
Chelsea: Yes. How fun.
Codey: Tough luck.
Codey: Um, the next family is Licenids.
Codey: Uh, these are the blues or the gossamer winged butterflies.
Codey: I love this family because 75% of them are what is known as mermecophylus, which means ant loving.
Codey: So they either the larvae either eat the caterpillars, either eat ant larvae, or the caterpillars will be deposited near an ant colony, or like as an egg, they'll be deposited, and then they'll hatch, and then they'll be near an ant colony, and they kind of will send some type of signal that makes it so the ants want to take them into their colony.
Codey: And then they will induce the ants to feed them.
Codey: And they basically just get fed by the ants until they're ready to pupate and then they like crawl out and pupate and then become a butterfly.
Chelsea: Wow.
Chelsea: That's crazy.
Codey: But so many of these.
Codey: And there's a lot of, because answer, we'll talk about it later, but ants are so ubiquitous.
Codey: They're everywhere.
Codey: They're so successful.
Codey: There are a lot.
Codey: of mermecophilus, uh, organisms, whether it's a fungus or a, there are beetles that they live entirely in ant nests.
Codey: Um, there are flies that, um, one thing that we learned in Costa Rica is that there's this family of flies that lays, so they are parasitoids of there's some species in the family that are parasitoids of ants.
Codey: And one ant.
Codey: could have been parasitised by 5 different flies, like 5 different species of this one family, because like one will specialise in the head, and one specialises in the legs, and one specialises in the thorax.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: And so like, And they also, so these are forward flies, P-H-O-R-I-D-A-E.
Chelsea: Oh my goodness.
Codey: And they, some of them are actually known as ant decapitating flies because they will, like, use their, they'll lay their egg like in the ant's neck.
Codey: And then chewed through the ants neck a little bit, I think, in some way.
Codey: And then the ant's head falls off, but then the larvae's like been deposited in it, and then the larvae will just eat the ant's like brain. And like all of that.
Chelsea: Well, that's a circle of life, baby.
Codey: Yeah, it's it's nuts.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Uh, so, so, but these, the thing that is just so interesting to me about Mermecophyllus butterflies, have, have, they've just like, they've gone vegan, right?
Codey: They're like, we eat plants and we, our larvae eat plants and we eat plants and that's, and like we eat flour.
Codey: We love flowers.
Codey: And then lycinids or like hold my beer.
Codey: I'm gonna revert.
Chelsea: Yeah, I'm eating my host.
Codey: Like, I'm gonna revert to having, like, it's either being carnivorous or just being parasitic on these.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Yeah, there's always an exception.
Codey: There's always an exception.
Chelsea: The ants don't discriminate.
Chelsea: They like, oh, you're part of us now.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: And this is how they get rewarded.
Codey: You smell right.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Like, it's usually that the lycenid caterpillars will emit a fair, like, um, emit like a smell or something that will be.
Codey: Yeah, it's nuts.
Codey: Um, that.
Codey: Oh, sorry, did you like that one?
Codey: Okay.
Codey: Um, so that is the butterflies that I'm going to talk about.
Codey: I'm going to move on to the moths now.
Codey: So moths can be identified differentiated from butterflies because they're antennae are not clubbed.
Codey: And often the males have plumose antenna, which is feathery.
Codey: So if you've ever seen a male, um, what you think is a butterfly or a moth and it's got these big feathers coming out of its head.
Codey: It's a moth and it's male.
Codey: Um, Yeah.
Chelsea: They're always in our mudroom, all the time, every night.
Codey: The big ones?
Chelsea: Going to that light.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Oh, that's so cool.
Codey: Yeah, they're very drawn to lights.
Codey: So moths are also, for the most part, butterflies are active in the day and moths are active in the night.
Codey: So a lot of moths, because they're, they don't mean to have these like bright showy colours.
Codey: They're not trying to attract based on a physical appearance.
Codey: It's usually through pheromones.
Codey: Um, They'll be really drab too.
Codey: So there's there's a lot of brown.
Codey: There's a lot of like lighter colours, like you're, yeah, you're not, there are not that many mods that have like blue or red or yellow or anything like that.
Chelsea: Yeah, we have like the yellowish looking one.
Codey: There are some, but it's not as common.
Codey: Um, and they're also because they're nocturnal and active during the night.
Codey: They usually use the moon to fly, um, and to orient their flight. And any light outside is a big moon to them.
Codey: So.
Chelsea: Boy, is that making me emotional?
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: I'm like, oh.
Codey: It is unfortunate.
Chelsea: The moon brought you here.
Codey: Um, light pollution is one of the ways that we are impacting not just insects, but like wildlife in general.
Codey: Um, so every time you drive by a stadium and you see, it's like nighttime and there's not a single thing happening and there's these giant huge stadium lights on.
Codey: Shake your fist because it's really frustrating.
Chelsea: I know, then you see the swarm of bugs around it, probably thinking like, oh, this is where I need to be right now.
Codey: They shouldn't.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Um, so some of the moths that I've pointed, uh, pulled out.
Codey: So there's the bagworm moths, which are the family psycheady.
Codey: So the larvae will create bags or cases out of sticks that help them camouflage.
Codey: So then you might just see like a little bundle of sticks, just like walking around.
Codey: Um, and this is, yeah, this is the type of moth that the Pokemon Burmy is based on.
Chelsea: They don't mind me.
Chelsea: Okay, hate it.
Codey: Because Burmie, like, like, depending on where a Burmie is, it will build different a different type of case.
Codey: And then,
Chelsea: Yeah, it was a different colour.
Codey: And also female bagworms.
Codey: So some species of female by worms, like they, they will, they might not even have, they might not even, like, Winners in that, because I don't know if that's true.
Codey: Period.
Codey: I might be conflating uh 2 different things.
Codey: Um, so then there's this other family of moths that kind of takes this to the next level.
Codey: So, the family is uh, cosmopter, terridity, and the genus specifically is hyposmocoma, and there is an uncurrently unnamed, but has been mentioned, and we know of it, and they're working on describing it, species within this genus, that is called the bone collector caterpillar.
Chelsea: That is metal as heck.
Codey: And this is just, so this is from the article, and I've linked the article if y'all want to see it.
Codey: The article, um, that kind of talks about these because this is from Hawaii. Um, and some of the researchers that that found this thing.
Codey: They did a press release.
Codey: And, uh, quote, however, while its cousins adorn themselves with sticks and shells for camouflage, the bone collector decorates its case with weevil heads, beetle abdomens and moulted spider exoskeletons.
Chelsea: That is so cool.
Codey: I have no idea what, like, nature go home, you're drunk.
Codey: Like, why?
Codey: Why?
Chelsea: Making things up at this point.
Codey: Like this moth was just like, mm, y'all have some lame stuff.
Codey: I like these beetleheads.
Codey: Like, imagine, imagine.
Chelsea: Let me just uh, collect some bones.
Codey: Like being a caterpillar and just walking through.
Codey: I guess there's that like meme of like someone looking at different things and like, mm, no, no.
Codey: And then they see like this, this caterpillar sees a weevil head and is like, yeah.
Codey: That's what I want.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: Sweet horrors beyond my imagination.
Codey: Yeah, so.
Chelsea: That's so cool.
Codey: Want to shout that out.
Chelsea: That is so, so cool.
Codey: Um, I also wanted to mention silk moths.
Codey: So there is the family bombicity, uh, which has the species bombix mori in it.
Codey: And that species is the domestic silk moth that has been used for nearly 5000 years in China for silk production.
Codey: Um, and it has been completely domesticated by them now.
Codey: Bombix Mori specifically is the domesticated version, I think, domesticated species.
Codey: And they basically raise these things.
Codey: And then I think once the, um, what they're using is the silk that is the cocoon.
Codey: So I think the, the larva, the caterpillar will make a cocoon, and then once it emerges as a moth, they'll take that cocoon and that's what they'll use to make silk because it's, it's, I mean, it's already there.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: It's already silk.
Codey: They're basically just deconstructing it so that they can use it for their own purposes.
Codey: Um, but this is an, uh, this has been and continues to be an incredibly huge, um, like, product that comes out of China.
Codey: Um, So I just, I have to I have to shout it out.
Codey: Oh, we do have silk moths elsewhere in the world.
Codey: Um, like the Saturneids in North America.
Codey: I mean, they're not just in North America, but they the biggest, they are the biggest moths in North America.
Codey: So the Saturnid moths include like the Atlas moths, the Cecropia moths, Polyphemus moths, like some of these are just really, really big moths.
Codey: Um, and they're real fun.
Codey: I once was walking.
Codey: I was doing research in the woods.
Codey: And I was just like walking through trees.
Codey: I had to like push trees aside, like young trees aside to like get to where I was going and kind of weave it, ducking and weaving it through this undergrowth.
Codey: And I like come upon just a giant moth that had just probably emerged because she was still very thick.
Codey: They usually emerge and then they poop.
Codey: Um,
Codey: It's called a maconium.
Codey: Uh, the babies do it too.
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: I've heard.
Codey: Um, but they emerge and then they, so I don't think she'd, she had uh, done that yet.
Codey: And she was still unfurling her wings.
Chelsea: Fresh out of it.
Codey: Yeah, fresh out of it.
Codey: They basically crawl up and then they pump their wings up because their wings are all crumpled.
Codey: And like the wings were not fully like uncrumpled.
Codey: But it was just a beautiful Cecropium off.
Codey: These are red and white giant moths.
Codey: And I was just like, what is this?
Codey: I hadn't ever seen one of those before.
Chelsea: Hello.
Codey: Um, so cool.
Codey: And, uh, yeah, uh, the largest moth is also in the family Saturnity, and it's the Atlas moth.
Chelsea: That's really cool.
Codey: And it's endemic to Asia. And, uh, again, animal crossing.
Chelsea: Yep.
Codey: We know all about the Atlas.
Chelsea: I always wonder about like the, the species that they chose for animal crossing because I have a friend who's a palaeontologist and sometimes I'll send him like screenshots of my museum and then he'll just tell me about them and I'm like, wow.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Cool.
Codey: Some of them make sense, and it is really funny, like, they'll have ones like that where it's like the Atlas Moth, and I'm like, yes, period.
Codey: That is uh, a moth.
Codey: And then they'll have other ones where it's like, bumblebee.
Codey: And I'm like, okay, there's like a 100 bumblebee species.
Codey: So, like, which one is? Or, like, stag beetle.
Codey: And I'm like, okay.
Chelsea: Dang Beetle.
Chelsea: They try.
Chelsea: They try to diversify it a little bit, but.
Codey: It's just hard.
Codey: Um, but speaking of Beatles,
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: We'll move on to the Beatles now.
Codey: So coleoptera is the name of the order, and coleoptera means sheath wing.
Codey: And this, they are so named because they're 4 wings.
Codey: So there's normally 4 pairs of wings, the 4 or like front wings and the hind wings.
Codey: And in beetles, the 4 wings, so the front ones are modified into a sheath, uh, known as the elytra.
Codey: If you've ever played Minecraft, you know that the elytra are pretty dope.
Codey: You can fly with them.
Codey: Um, but basically these provide a hardcover that they can then fold their their hindwings that they used to fly like up under there.
Codey: So some people think that beetles don't even have wings because, I mean, 9 times at a time when you see a beetle, it's like crawling around.
Codey: But if you bother it enough, it'll, it'll open its, um, elytra and the wings are like spring loaded.
Codey: They like pop out and then they'll fly and they are not good flyers.
Codey: Beatles suck at flying.
Chelsea: No.
Codey: They're so clumsy.
Chelsea: Yeah, we've seen a few where like the kids will be looking at it and then it'll just kind of pop up and they're like, what?
Codey: It can be very, it can be very startling.
Chelsea: And then it kind of bumbles away.
Codey: Um.
Codey: This is a quote from uh, Wikipedia, the roughly 400,000 species make up about 40% of all arthropod species so far described, and about 25% of all animals.
Codey: One in 4 animals.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Beatles be awesome.
Codey: Um, So far that we know of.
Chelsea: So far that we know of.
Codey: So some papers, uh, some of the more recent papers that are trying to get an estimate of what the true diversity is, have estimated around 1500000 Beetle species, which means that we haven't even found a 3rd of them.
Chelsea: Wow.
Chelsea: We're so...
Codey: We are not even a 3rd of the way through the Beatles.
Codey: and the Beatles are everywhere.
Codey: Um, there's about 170 described families.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: And I just love, uh, there, there was an evolutionary biologist named J.B.S Halding that, uh, when he was looking at, uh, thinking, he was talking about theologians and Christians, and as an evolutionary biologist, he was talking to them and said, well, of, of your god, uh, he must have an inordinate fondness for beetles because there's a heck ton of these.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: But the exact quote is an inordinate fondness for beetles.
Codey: And that is just, we just, God was a bug collector.
Chelsea: God was a book collector.
Codey: God loved bugs, you guys.
Codey: So if you're, if you are a true, true Christian, you should probably, uh, love bugs a little bit more.
Codey: Not fear them as much.
Chelsea: Oh, you're a true Christian.
Chelsea: What are your 10 favourite beetles?
Codey: Oh my god, I almost, I was taking a drink of water and I almost spit it across.
Codey: Okay.
Codey: Um, let me see where I want to do.
Codey: The, um, of Beatles, the most diverse Beatle family are the rove beetles, uh, Staphylinity.
Codey: These.
Codey: I forgot to make notes for this, so I'm just gonna riff.
Codey: Um, these Beatles are often, uh, detritivores.
Codey: They often will eat like things that are breaking down and decaying.
Codey: Um, and they just, they have so many different shapes and sizes.
Codey: There are so many families or things that we thought were an entirely different family, that it's like, mm, nope, it's a rope beetle, actually.
Codey: Um,
Codey: We make jokes in the museum that I've worked at and then also just museums, uh, elsewhere that people, I know, some of my friends, where if you can't, if you're trying to identify a beetle, if you're going through the dichotomous key and trying to figure out which beetle it is and you're just stumped, it's probably a rove beetle.
Codey: It's probably just a really weird one.
Chelsea: Just throw it over there.
Codey: Because, like, the thing about Rove Beatles is that the one of they don't really have a quote unquote defining characteristic because the what used to be considered the defining characteristic is that they're Elytra are incredibly short.
Codey: So they basically have, like, for most beetles, when you think of a beetle, you don't see any of the abdomen, because the entire abdomen is covered with that sheath, that, um, they're elytra, but staphylinids have a really shortened elytra.
Codey: So some of their abdominal segments are exposed, usually up to 4 of them, 4 or more of them.
Codey: But then, of course, because there's always an exception, people found rove beetles that don't have that necessarily.
Codey: There are some that are like, and they're usually like flat and thin, and then of course we found some that are like chonky.
Codey: Um, oh, they normally are pretty sleek.
Codey: Nope, we found some that are really like ribbed or ridged.
Codey: like they have like a lot of,
Chelsea: Out into the church.
Codey: Yeah, it's like, nope, they did that too.
Codey: And we basically, you know, from, from just looking at them morphologically and and trying to figure out what they are, just how they look, they might seem like a different species.
Codey: But then looking at the DNA.
Codey: We realise, oh, no, they're still, they're still within, within this family.
Codey: Um, So this family might get broken up eventually.
Codey: We don't know, or it might or we might, it might continue to subsume all of the other Beatles.
Codey: Um, we don't know.
Codey: But they're really cool.
Codey: Um, and then I just had to shout out my favourite Beatle family.
Codey: These are, so it's the family cryptofagedy.
Codey: Uh, that name means feeding in hidden places because for a long time.
Codey: They really didn't know what they ate.
Codey: So they were like, I don't know.
Codey: I don't know what they eat.
Codey: So let's just call them.
Chelsea: Something is sustaining them somewhere.
Codey: Yeah, I don't know what they eat.
Codey: So let's just call them unknown eating, like crypto fagid.
Codey: That's just what we're going to call them.
Codey: Um, but they are, uh, both the adults and the larvae appear to feed exclusively on fungus, but the fungus can be in some really weird situations, like, the fungus that grows on animal fur that has been shed or bird feathers that have been shed.
Codey: Um, And then some also do like rotting wood, whatever.
Codey: And so that has given them their common name of silken fungus beetles.
Codey: And they're called silken because they have they have a good amount of usually hair, like really fine hair all over their body.
Codey: And they also are just this, they're usually this little, um, like, light caramel colour.
Codey: They really cute.
Codey: But the big thing.
Codey: If you're not sold, I have to refer you to the genus Antherophagus, which means flower eating.
Codey: These are known as the bumblebee riding beetles.
Chelsea: Adorable.
Codey: So I have, I have put a picture of this in the show notes.
Chelsea: This photo needs to be everywhere.
Codey: So either go look at it or just look up this genus.
Codey: Um, or just look up Bumblebee Riding beetles, uh, specifically look it up in Bugguide.net, which is the website, uh, that a lot of us, that a lot of North American entomologists use.
Codey: There's a lot of really good photos on there of these things.
Codey: So what they do is they will sometimes cling to either the mouth parts or the antennae or the legs, whatever, of bumblebees, so that they can be carried to the nests because they specialise on fungus that is growing on detritus inside of bumblebee nests.
Chelsea: Interesting.
Codey: But they are just so, so basically the image for people who might not, um, look, might not see it or what, so it's basically a bumblebee and her tongue is out, like fully.
Codey: out, like her tongue is just like real straight out.
Codey: And on the end of it, there's just this beetle that is just maunched down.
Chelsea: I am enamoured with this.
Chelsea: It is so adorable.
Codey: Just looks like this beat hole.
Chelsea: And the people also look super offended too.
Codey: Yeah, this beetle's like, excuse me, leave me alone.
Chelsea: Do you mind?
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Just take me to your house.
Chelsea: Take me home.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Codey: So that's my favourite family of Beatles.
Codey: I just had to shout them out.
Codey: Um, we also have, so now moving on to another family.
Codey: There's the family Sal Pingidi.
Codey: I chose these because I love, these are very similar to staffs where like they kind of do everything.
Codey: Um, and this is likely a junk drawer family.
Codey: So I've talked in previous episodes about junk drawer, taxa, or waste, waste basket, taxons, or whatever, where it's basically, if you can't, if you can't describe it in any particular way, that it can fit into your category, your nice little categories that you've made, if it doesn't fit into any of those, you just put it into the other family, basically, or like the other, it's one of those.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: And that's what cell pinges in my mind are.
Codey: Um, There are, uh, there's a person who studies Staphalinids, who works.
Codey: One of my friends works at the Carnegie Museum of Natural History in Pittsburgh.
Codey: Her name is Ainsley Sego.
Codey: And she posted on Blue Sky, this like thread about Sal Pingids, that haunts me to this day, where she was like, Sal Pingids can just do anything.
Codey: And she posted a picture of something and she's like, what Beetle family do you think this is?
Codey: And then the next comment or something was like, nope, it's not a, a ladybird beetle, a ladybug.
Codey: It's actually a cell pinged.
Codey: Or like, oh, you think this is a weevil?
Codey: Nope, it's a cell pinged.
Codey: And it was just like, what the heck?
Codey: Like it's just another.
Codey: frigging anomaly.
Codey: And I'm just like, are you freaking kidding me?
Codey: And then,
Chelsea: Oh, you thought?
Codey: And then as I was looking in my personal notes for this family to see what I had, I just, I just took from my notes exactly what I wrote.
Codey: Um, so the 1st part, the 1st 2 statements is Beetle talk.
Codey: So just, I just wanted to let you guys know, this is the type of words that we use to describe, um, different Beatles.
Codey: So, uh, South Pinges have closed procoxyl cavities and laterally closed misocoxyl cavities.
Codey: So that's some of that speak.
Codey: Um, but then I have a really fun note that says head lacking a neck, like a football player.
Chelsea: Oh my.
Codey: I don't know where.
Codey: So I don't, I didn't, I didn't write where I, like it, it was probably when I was at Beatles school in Arizona that I just, like, was taking notes and I just wrote this down, but just, like, what the heck?
Chelsea: Take that.
Codey: Um, and then I also wrote that the subfamilies are all probably distinct families question mark, and that's that, again, since this is a drunk drawer tags on, like, things that are thrown into it are probably their own thing.
Codey: We just haven't, we'll just get to that later.
Chelsea: They're like we'll get to that later.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Um, okay.
Codey: And then the last one.
Codey: I got to fix it.
Codey: Okay.
Codey: The last Beetle family I want to talk about is Kirkulianade.
Codey: So these are the weevils.
Codey: I had to mention the weevils.
Codey: Um, The weevils are well known for uh, their boots and their snoots.
Codey: So if you go to the Reddit subreddit, our weevil time, so R slash weevil time, this is an entire subreddit that's just dedicated to people posting photos about weevils.
Codey: And like a lot of these people are not entomologists.
Codey: They just find.
Chelsea: No, they just, they have a passion for this.
Codey: They just find them and they're like, I found one.
Codey: And talking to non-entomologists, if I mention weevils.
Chelsea: Oh my god, I'm sorry, I'm on it now.
Codey: They're like, oh.
Codey: You, yeah, you looked a photo.
Chelsea: Look at these divas.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Uh, people, even a toxin non-entomologist, and I just mentioned weevils.
Codey: And they like, oh, boots and snoots.
Codey: So I had to, I had to blurb that.
Chelsea: Boots of?
Codey: Um, and they say boobs since newts because for boots, uh, they have really large uh, feet.
Codey: So each of their leg, uh, each of their tarsi, like the, the, um, part of the leg that is the farthest away from the body, each of those are like clubbed almost, like they have like really big ridges on them and like this, they're pads on either side of the leg.
Codey: So, and it looks like boots.
Codey: Some of them can look like they got some really big boots on.
Codey: got large feet.
Codey: And then snoots.
Chelsea: I got their high heels clanking on the ground.
Codey: They got they got those heels, man.
Codey: And then snoots because they have a long, what is it called, a rostrum.
Codey: Uh, it's the nose, basically.
Codey: And a lot of them have their antenna coming off of their rostrum.
Codey: So instead of the antennae coming off like near the eyes or whatever.
Codey: They basically have this a long, like, long nose, and somewhere down that ridge, they're in Jenny.
Codey: And they're just...
Chelsea: Such a weird, I love it.
Codey: They're so weird.
Chelsea: I'm obsessed with this
Codey: and I love them.
Codey: And so I wanted to mention them, but I also wanted to mention that this, there's a great example of, um, using uh, a digital platform.
Codey: monitor biodiversity.
Codey: So I talked about eye naturalist, which is an application that you can use that you can basically take photos of bugs in real time and like you quote unquote catch them all or whatever.
Codey: It doesn't even have to be bugs.
Codey: It can be plants, it can be animals.
Codey: It's just any type of life.
Codey: It could be a fungus.
Codey: And so, uh, the, the title, this article, this, I don't, I think this is a journal manuscript, uh, quote, rediscovery of the greater chestnut weevil highlights the power of digital platforms in biodiversity research and conservation.
Codey: And the story basically is that we entomologists thought that the greater chestnut weevil was extinct, because of the fact that a lot of the American chestnut, the tree, was wiped out by this blight, um, that occurred in the last like 100 years or whatever.
Codey: So there are significantly fewer chestnuts now than there ever were across North America.
Codey: And the greater chestnut weevil specialises on their on, um, their seeds.
Codey: So, because, um, the chestnut's gone, the weevil was pretty much gone as well.
Codey: And it hadn't been seen, and I want to say 30 years, a 30 or 40 years, until someone, like a Beatle expert was on a naturalist and was looking at, uh, a closely related species, like the pictures that people had posted of a closely related species and they were like, wait a minute, that's not, that's not that species.
Codey: That's his other species.
Codey: And they got in contact with the person, and then they went to the area that the person had taken a photo of and gone to the chestnuts that are still, because some, there are still some chestnuts holding on, and they went to the chestnuts in the area, and they found some of these things.
Codey: So this is just another example of they wouldn't have even known that this thing was still alive, like, and still, um, not extinct if these people hadn't posted it on my naturalist. So, go post things on INAT, you guys.
Chelsea: Wow.
Chelsea: Now post some Beatles.
Codey: Okay.
Codey: Moving on to flies.
Codey: So flies are in the order diptera, which is just 2 wing, die, terra.
Codey: Um, and they're known that because they're hind wings instead of having 4 wings.
Codey: Their hind wings have been significantly reduced to just orienteering appendages known as halt tears.
Codey: Um, So they only actually have 2 wings.
Codey: There are about 150 described species of flies in about 160 families.
Codey: And the 1st family that I felt obligated to mention is mosquitoes.
Codey: So mosquitoes in their family, celicity, and they are well renowned because they are the deadliest animal.
Codey: Um, because of specifically the diseases that they vector.
Chelsea: I was going to say I was at the, like, malaria and stuff that they carry.
Codey: Yeah, so they themselves do not kill people, but they vector things like malaria and dengue and a bunch of other diseases, like different species will vector different things.
Codey: Um, they vector so many different things that then kill people.
Codey: But if it were not for the mosquito, like if the mosquitoes weren't in existence, these diseases would not spread.
Codey: So they are a required component for these diseases to spread and for these viruses to kill people.
Codey: So for that reason, they are considered the deadliest animals.
Chelsea: Wow, interesting.
Codey: So they are incredibly important for veterinary entomology, and there's a lot of work that is being done, like with the sterile insect technique, where they are releasing sterilised males so that they will mate with a female, and then the female will not be able to produce viable young.
Codey: Um, there's also certain traps that people are trying to develop to put out for certain species of, of, um, mosquito, there are, um, like different, I don't know, I'm kind of blanking.
Codey: But there's just like so many different things, different avenues of research within vector entomology because of the mosquito.
Codey: Um, and my personal story with mosquitoes is that I almost caught one that was purple and blue in Costa Rica.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: So I put a photo of this, of this, um, mosquito in the show notes, but the species is Sabethy's Sianius, um, S-A-B, E-T-H-E-S, C-Y-A-N-E-U-S.
Codey: Um, and it sure is, like, it is, in the photo that I've posted, it's just, you can see most of the blue, but they also have these, like, feathered legs, um, and the legs are, like, purple.
Codey: And,
Chelsea: They're very metallic looking.
Codey: Yeah, and a couple people, when I was at fly school, caught a couple of these.
Chelsea: It's cool.
Codey: And so when I saw one, I was like, oh, I want it, but I I meant I lost it, which is fine.
Codey: But it's just super, really super interesting thing.
Codey: Um, along.
Codey: With mosquitoes, people often hear of mosquito hawks, which refers to crane flies or those within the family to Pulidae.
Codey: Um,
Codey: These are very clumsy flights.
Codey: Like, I don't know if you, like these, they basically just look like big mosquitoes.
Codey: Um, and people used to say it was an urban legend that they eat mosquitoes.
Codey: Um, so it's not that they're like a mosquito, but they eat them.
Codey: That is not true.
Codey: Um, They eat other things, but they're just clumsy as
Codey: Um, and there are like 5 families of crane flies that, uh, the crane fly specialists are still trying to figure out like, okay, are they distinct families?
Codey: Are they all just one family?
Codey: So this is, it's kind of a couple things.
Codey: So I love this, this group because it's just an example of an existing like conundrum of, okay, what, how are they related?
Codey: And it really just takes studying more of them?
Codey: to find that out?
Codey: And my personal anecdote, uh, with crane flies is that I found one in Costa Rica that is likely a new genus.
Codey: So I collected this crane fly in Costa Rica.
Codey: I thought it was really interesting because it was like orange.
Codey: So they're normally very drab colours, but this one was orange and its wings had this really weird colour pattern on it.
Codey: I've posted a link of the exact specimen that I collected that the Dr. Matt Breton, who is the, one of the instructors of the of the fly school.
Codey: Um, he had a really good camera setup and he had a DSLR like camera staging area to take photos of some of the specimens that we caught.
Codey: So I actually just brought him the fly alive and he then took photos of it.
Codey: And then we euthanised it by freezing it.
Codey: And then I mounted it. And it is now in the, um, Costa Rica Natural History Museum.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: But when Matt, when Dr. Bertone posted it to a naturalist, like, um, uh, crane fly specialist was like, whoa, like, I don't know what this is.
Codey: And he was like, I mean, it's probably this genus.
Codey: And then they reached back out and they were like, I looked up every single described of this gene, like species of this genus and it's not any of these things.
Codey: But and so they, they're still trying to figure it out.
Chelsea: That is so amazing.
Codey: There's, it's still an active like thing, but when I went to the big bug conference last year and I went to the Dipteras Society meeting, that's the fly, the fly people's meeting.
Codey: Um, Dr. Bertone mentioned that this is possibly a new genus.
Codey: And I was like, whoa.
Codey: That's crazy.
Codey: Um, Costa Rica, so much undescribed diverse flies, man.
Chelsea: Amazing.
Codey: Um, speaking of Costa Rica, I have to shout out um, another family that was collect that we collected there that was really interesting.
Codey: So, um, the picture wing flies or the Euladeids, um, we have them here as well.
Codey: They just have, they often have dark colouration on their wings.
Codey: So instead of their wings just being clear.
Codey: They have like patterns or splotches or whatever, which is why they're known as picture winged flies.
Codey: Um, But we found, and they're normally pretty, pretty simple, like they just, other than that, they look like a normal fly, but we found this one in Costa Rica.
Codey: Which was already a described species, but it is a
Codey: Do you see this photo?
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: describe to the listeners what you're seeing.
Chelsea: Uh, so it looks like a bug holding up a stick, but I feel like those are its eyes.
Codey: Those are its eyes.
Chelsea: So it looks like I never had shark or something.
Codey: So yeah, it's like a hammerhead shark fly.
Codey: But the eye stalks, like, are like twice the fly's body leg.
Chelsea: That is so creep, like.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: And this.
Chelsea: They they see everything or nothing.
Codey: Dude, yeah, so this is a male and the males have this sexual selection of just being, um, like eyes go big, right?
Codey: Like, that's like their whole, like, my eyes are bigger than yours.
Codey: And they basically, when the males are fighting over a female or whatever, they like, they just stare at each other, like face off each other. And then I don't know how they decide which is superior.
Codey: But so that's, this is just sexual selection gone absolutely nuts.
Codey: because they have these huge stocks and then the eyes are on the end of the stock.
Chelsea: This is okay, when I 1st saw it, I'm like, oh, is it holding up a stick? And I'm like, no, that's his eyes.
Codey: No, it just, I, and so someone, someone found this, uh, at the lights, actually.
Chelsea: What the heck?
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: So rather than being in a trap or like being out like in the jungle, like in Costa Rica, it was just at the light at the nature centre. We were...
Chelsea: He wanted you to, he wanted to be found.
Codey: Yeah, he was like, hey what's up?
Codey: And it was really funny because we actually in the room where Dr. Bertone was taking photos because this is another one that Dr. Bertone took photos of.
Codey: Um, in the room that Dr. Berton was taking photos, this fly actually got out.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: But it's a closed room.
Chelsea: Did y'all see the bug with the crazy eyes?
Codey: Yeah, but it's a closed room and like those eyes, like in the shape that he is, like we, we, we, we always knew where it was.
Chelsea: Walking around?
Codey: We were like, he's right, he right there.
Chelsea: I got my eye on you.
Codey: So we had to catch him, I think, twice.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Chelsea: He's got to show off his eyes to his lady friends.
Chelsea: Come on, he's got stuff to do.
Codey: Yeah, there were, we might, I think we caught a female as well, but like that male, though, that is just, it was absolutely nuts.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: So do the females have the smaller ones or like do all the, yeah.
Codey: Yes, the females just don't even have it, just like peacocks.
Chelsea: Oh, okay.
Codey: Like the females just are block.
Chelsea: They're here to impress the females.
Codey: Exactly.
Codey: Um, No.
Chelsea: I don't know how you bow.
Chelsea: That's a Halloween costume idea.
Codey: Oh my gosh, it totally is.
Codey: I don't, like you could just, you would just get like paper towel holders or like the paper towel rolls, like, and can, like, just make those.
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Codey: I should probably I should do that.
Chelsea: I'm thinking about it now.
Codey: Um, okay.
Codey: Another fly family, uh, moving on to just basic fly families, less less that I have, less than, okay.
Codey: I'm saying them not because I have a cool anecdote, but because I think they're people will often interact with them, um, so one of them is a houseflies.
Codey: So this is the family muscady or muscade, depending on how you pronounce it.
Codey: I usually, it's a silent sea for me normally, because you don't say science, when you say science, you don't say science.
Codey: So it's a it's a silent scene for me, y'all.
Chelsea: Giant.
Codey: Um, But the larvae feed in on dung, carrion soils, nests, decaying vegetation, um, you know, an adult will come and lay eggs in your in your trash can, basically.
Codey: Like they will, and that's why they are called houseflies because they are just so ubiquitous in our houses.
Codey: Um, the adults of some of these species can bite.
Codey: Not a lot of the North American ones.
Codey: And they might passively spread agents of typhoid, dysentery, anthrax, and African sleeping sickness.
Chelsea: I'm looking at this.
Chelsea: I'm like, oh, that's in our house.
Chelsea: Cool.
Codey: A lot of these are not.
Codey: So like, a lot of the, um, disease agents, like the disease has to be active in your area for it to even be a problem.
Codey: So.
Codey: For most for the most part in North America, we're good.
Chelsea: Dissentery's making a comeback, though.
Codey: Is it?
Codey: Oh my gosh.
Codey: Oh, well, yeah, there we go.
Codey: If you have houseflies, maybe uh, be careful.
Codey: Um, And then another thing, as I was looking up the week looking out the Wikipedia for this, uh, another example of entomophage or eating bugs, um, the quote here is, however, housefly larvae are as nutritious as fish meal and could be used to convert waste to insect-based animal feed for farmed fish and livestock.
Codey: So they are a very effective thing to feed to fish if you have like a hatchery situation or to farmed livestock, other livestock.
Codey: So cool.
Codey: Especially because they grow they reproduce so fast and so prolifically.
Codey: Um, that this is a, an organism that would be very easy to farm itself.
Codey: Like, it's very easy for us to, like, create a bunch of housewives. Housewives, that we could then turn into something else.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: So it's a good, uh, good possibility for future insect farming.
Codey: And then the last fly family are the Drosophalids, um, or the vinegar flies.
Codey: Sometimes people call these fruit flies, but there's another fly family that are called the fruit flies.
Codey: This is Tifridity, but Drosophilids are mostly attracted to vinegar, which of course some fruits when they start fermenting.
Codey: They smell like vinegar, so or they are vinegar, whatever.
Codey: Um, but the biggest thing about, uh, Drosophalids that I wanted to mention is the species Drosophylla Milanagaster, because this was the 1st insect genome to be entirely sequenced, uh, in 2000.
Codey: And just off them, Lanagaster remains one of the most studied organisms, because it is a perfect, it's a very good organism for study.
Codey: Um, particularly in genetics, developmental biology, and environmental mutagen- mutagenesis, um, which I had to look that up because I was like, excuse me.
Codey: And environmental mutagenesis is just the study of how environmental agents, like chemicals or radiation, alter your genetic material, often leading to mutation.
Codey: Makes sense.
Codey: But Drossophil and Lanagaster, because we've already, we already understand the genome in its entirety, we can now go in with technologies like CRISPR, where they can go and edit some of the genes and we can actually start understanding, okay, this gene, when we messed with it, this is what happened.
Codey: So this gene is important for the development of eyes or whatever or like this type of behaviour or what have you.
Codey: And this isn't necessarily going to lead to big things for people.
Codey: But it has helped us understand, um, other insects.
Codey: And by understanding the genome and understanding how messing with certain uh, sections of the of your genome can impact like the the health of the organism or something, we can actually, that's one of the ways that they do like steril insect technique, for example.
Codey: Um, and I'm pretty sure that they did that with, um, Drosophila as a as a base base study organism.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Because so many of insects, so many of the insects have like their genome was very, very similar, just with a couple tweaks, right?
Codey: So, this is just a great study organism to continue to look into all that.
Chelsea: Huh?
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Okay, last order.
Codey: Uh, Hymenoptera means membrane wing.
Codey: Um, and their, I'm not entirely sure why it has that name.
Codey: Um, there's a lot, there's not, there's a lot of reasons why people think it might have that name, but there's no distinct ones, so I'm not going to mention them, but one thing that distinguishes this family from others is that they have, um, hooks on their hind wings that connect to the fore wing that functionally creates 2 wings.
Codey: So instead of flying and having their 4 wings flap all over the place, like crazy and like, um, um, disconnected, their hind wings will just kind of like click, it's like a Velcro mechanism almost, like into their 4 wings and then they will fly.
Chelsea: Oh cool.
Codey: Um, it incredibly vastly improves their air dynamics.
Chelsea: Like some aerodynamic.
Codey: Which like when people say, oh, bumblebee wings wouldn't be able to hold bumblebees up.
Codey: blah, blah, blah, whatever.
Codey: Um, They can if you hook them together, which they have that.
Chelsea: Right.
Codey: Um, in addition, female hymenopterans typically have a special ovipo- uh, appendage known as an ovipositor for laying eggs.
Codey: And sometimes in some families, in some groups,
Codey: This ovipositor has been weaponized.
Codey: Um, and it's a stinger.
Chelsea: Oh wow.
Codey: So it, yeah, it has...
Codey: um, uh, hardened and also, uh, for some of them has an associated venom gland as well.
Codey: So it just really, they're going into the weapon realm with that.
Chelsea: Wow.
Chelsea: How long does it take for something to evolve like that?
Codey: Oh man.
Codey: Um, like 100s of 1000000s of years.
Chelsea: Many, many.
Codey: Yeah, for something like that to change, to evolve.
Codey: um,
Codey: And it was probably like the way that I would, I would think that that would have evolved would be something like, you know, they already had an ovipositor just for laying their eggs.
Codey: And then at one point, they started using that, like if something was attacking them.
Codey: They would like, it's just another appendage, another way to attack your attacker, right?
Codey: and like defend yourself.
Codey: So they were probably like hitting the or trying to stab their attacker with it or hit them with it or whatever.
Codey: And some organism.
Codey: Some individuals probably would have had, might have had like more hard.
Codey: Um, ovipositors for whatever reason.
Codey: And then those individuals would have been more successful at defending themselves and surviving.
Codey: And then that times a thousand.
Codey: And then you get to the point where they, it's, it's a stinger now and, uh, there's an open, there's like a, it's like a secondary thing.
Chelsea: Right.
Codey: Like, so the ovipositor is still there, but the stinger itself, um, is like completely, it might, might be completely different or it might still be just like one thing.
Codey: Um, but it usually is, has venom.
Codey: I don't know.
Codey: It's crazy.
Codey: Um, but many 100s of 1000000s of years.
Chelsea: Many of them, yeah.
Codey: Many, maybe two.
Chelsea: Maybe.
Codey: Um, Hi Minoptera have about 150,000 species, again, described.
Codey: Um, and about 150 families and uh, rough estimate of Hymenoptera from a couple papers is that there are likely over a 1000000 species.
Codey: So we're only at about 15% described.
Codey: If that is true.
Codey: Um, of those, we have the ants.
Codey: Um, the family formicity.
Codey: We already mentioned them and how crazy how they've pretty much taken over the world.
Codey: They're all over the place, and that has led to a lot of things relying on them and being Mermecophyllis and using them.
Codey: But answer you social, so that means that they have true use sociality of a of a queen, um, that produces young that then take care of her young, like continually.
Codey: Um, and for that reason they live in colonies.
Codey: And I think I, my favourites are the leaf cutter ants.
Codey: Um, some of those are really crazy.
Codey: We went when I was in Costa Rica.
Codey: You can see the paths.
Codey: Like, even if they're not active at the time, though, you like, they are almost always doing their leaf thing.
Codey: Um, There's like a, it's like a little trail.
Codey: Like imagine like a road.
Codey: And there's just, you can just see that there's like this road and then when you get like little, maybe 4 inch wide.
Chelsea: Yeah, I could just see where they were chomping.
Codey: Um, I don't know how inches relate to centimetres.
Codey: I, sorry.
Codey: Um, Oh, wait, I actually have a thing right here.
Codey: Maybe.
Chelsea: It's okay.
Chelsea: Cries in Canadian.
Codey: Cries in Canadian.
Codey: I actually have a thing right here.
Codey: 4 inches is 7 centimetres.
Codey: I think, I think, maybe.
Codey: Um, around there, maybe 10.
Codey: Um, But yeah, the a little path that's like that wide and it just meanders through.
Codey: And then when you get close enough to it, you see that it's also full of these ants going 2 ways.
Codey: Like, well, there's one trail going one way and one going the other, and some of them are carrying leaves because they will, um, chew, they'll go up to whatever tree they're, they're defoliating, and they will cut off a little bit of a leaf and then they'll take it back.
Codey: And some of them will construct tunnels out of that.
Codey: Some of them will actually farm that.
Codey: So they basically bring the leaves back.
Codey: A fungus grows on the leaf, and then they eat the fungus.
Codey: They literally farm.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: We thought we were the only organism that farmed, but was incorrect.
Chelsea: Or a farming.
Chelsea: Nope.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Um, yeah, answer crazy.
Codey: Uh, wasps.
Codey: So, people when when I say wasps, people think of predatory wasps, like, uh, social wasps, um, yellow jackets, um, hornets, things like that.
Codey: But they're the majority of wasps are parasitic.
Codey: So, like I mentioned earlier, they will lay an egg onto a host, whether or sometimes into a host.
Codey: Um, and some of them, there's some leaf mining wasps and flies, but they will actually lay an egg, like in between a leaf, like in the middle of a leaf.
Codey: So, you know how leaves are just a bundle of cells.
Codey: Um, like they like 30 cells deep or something and then you're at the, you're from the top of the leaf, uh, to the, to the other side of the leaf, and they will lay an egg in between that area, like in the middle of it.
Codey: And then you, uh, the larvae would then like eat a path.
Codey: like through the leaf, like a leaf mine.
Codey: Um, and so that's another way that things can be parasitic.
Codey: Um, but the main parasitic ones I wanted to talk about are gall wasps, which are in the family synipidi.
Codey: So these, and synipity includes mostly the oak gall wasps.
Codey: So these are wasps that uh, generate uh, induce the plant to create what is called a gall.
Codey: So the wasp will lay an egg.
Codey: And something about, I'm not, I don't know exactly how it all works, but that egg then induces the tree, the like branch, to create like a protective casing around it, because the tree is like, this is, um, bad and we want to make sure that our tissues, like the actual plant tissue is separated from whatever this is.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: So they will create like a ball.
Codey: And that's when you, that's what is known as a gall.
Codey: Um, and galls come in, there's so many weirdly shaped gulls.
Codey: There are some that look like weird, weird fruit.
Codey: There's some that are fuzzy.
Codey: There's some that are just, just, they just look like little, um, uh, swollen bits of of a leaf or of, of, uh, whatever.
Codey: There's so many different types of skulls.
Codey: But um, when the plant then creates that gall, the insect is then like, this is great.
Codey: Thank you.
Codey: Like, thanks for the home.
Codey: Like the, the larvae basically grows up in that it eats, um, that tissue that is created and as it eats more of the tissue.
Chelsea: Thanks.
Chelsea: So nice of you.
Codey: I think the plant produces more of the tissue.
Codey: Um, yeah, it's nuts.
Codey: And they Sinippids are not the only wasps that create galls or induce galls, but they sure do a lot of it.
Codey: And these wasps are tiny.
Codey: Like you would normally not, like the head of a pin, you normally would not see this wasp at all.
Chelsea: Really?
Codey: Um, however, they are not the tiniest.
Codey: The tiniest insect is a fairy wasp.
Codey: These are known as the family mimerity.
Codey: And these are, you literally have to look at a microscope.
Codey: Like I will have a via Petri dish of ethanol that has like a fairy wasp somewhere in it.
Codey: And I might see, I'm like, oh, there's like kind of a speck here and I'm like, oh, nope, that's like a bit of dirt.
Codey: And then I keep looking and I'm like, oh, there's another bit of dirt.
Codey: Nope, that's the wasp.
Codey: Like there's, they're so tiny and they're so cute.
Chelsea: Oh, I just looked it up.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: And their wings are also fringed in a really cute way, I think it's cute.
Chelsea: Yeah, like fuzzy.
Codey: Yeah, they're fuzzy.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: They look fuzzy because like the wing itself isn't just like what you when you imagine a wing, it's not like that.
Codey: It has like feathery bits coming off of it.
Codey: So they're super cute.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: So not all wasps have that black and yellow sort of. Feel to them?
Codey: Mm-mm, nope.
Codey: So that black and yellow fear is uh, the family Vespity, which are the social wasps.
Chelsea: No.
Codey: Um, and they are called social ops because they themselves are social, and they're not necessarily you social.
Codey: They're not the same type of sociality that ants and some bees have.
Codey: They might nest communally.
Codey: It might be that one of them has, um, like starts creating a nest and then lays an egg, like lays some egg and eggs and then takes care of the larvae.
Codey: But then there are other ones that might be like, this is a nice nest, and then she might also like use it. And so then they become kind of a communal organ, like colony rather than...
Chelsea: How they just kind of cohabitate.
Codey: Yeah, they basically cohabitate or they could be use social, some of the species are.
Codey: Um, And so, but all of this wasps, most of the wasps that have that social type of behaviour are within one family.
Codey: One of the over 150 families that exist, but that's what everyone thinks of.
Codey: And whenever people mention Yellowjackets to be and being scared of them.
Codey: I mean, super valid because it is scary and they hurt.
Codey: And, um, and they can really swarm you pretty intensely.
Codey: However, they are just protecting their house.
Codey: And I am of the mind that if their house is not in an inconvenient place.
Codey: Just let him go.
Codey: Just let him live.
Chelsea: Yeah, we have a nest near our, like on our house at the very top near the attic and I'm like, you know what?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Don't come in my house and I'll leave you alone.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Well, and even if they come in your house, like, I was walking through my house one time, and there was a really big, um, no, uh, wasp, and I was like, okay.
Codey: And but I know because I was not threatening her or I was, she was not trying to defend her nest or whatever.
Codey: I literally just put my finger down and she climbed on top of it and then I just took her outside and like put her on a leaf and she was fine.
Codey: Um, as long as you're not like actively trying to harm them, they won't.
Chelsea: Oh wow.
Chelsea: You're not swatting at them.
Codey: Exactly.
Codey: Um, and the majority of the wasps in this family investity are going to eat pest species in your garden.
Codey: So they will eat caterpillars that, or they will bring caterpillars back till they're young, like a couple different things that they do, but they will, they will basically reduce the amount of pests that are in your carbon.
Codey: So if you can leave them alone, that's great.
Codey: But also, I understand when people are scared of things, I get it.
Codey: But, um,
Chelsea: I think it's like the unpredictability a lot of people don't know like.
Codey: Yeah, so some of the yellow jackets have, um, like nests that hang that you can very clearly see.
Codey: It's like the paper wasps and stuff.
Codey: Like you can very clearly see like that is a nest that is hanging.
Codey: Some of them have make like mud nests and you're like cool.
Codey: There you are.
Codey: I got it.
Codey: I see you.
Codey: But then a lot of the yellow jackets will also nest underground.
Codey: those are the bad ones.
Chelsea: Oh, really?
Codey: Those are the ones that scare people the most because, and I mean, because you could just be walking.
Codey: And then if you step on where their nest is, um, if they haven't dug their nest down deep enough, and you step like on the soil around it, you might disturb within the nest and that's going to set them, um, one of them's probably going to emit alarm pheromone, and that's going to tell them like, oh, oh, heck, like something's happening, and then they're going to immobilise.
Codey: And you are, unfortunately, the largest thing in the area that they think probably, and you probably did cause it.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: It was you.
Codey: It was you.
Codey: And so yeah, they'll come out and they'll they'll swarm you and they'll sting and they'll bite. And, um, honey bees are actually the only bees that have a barbed sting where it comes out, like once they sting you, it comes out of their body and they die.
Codey: So most bees and wasps.
Codey: If they sting you, they're they're going to keep stinging you.
Codey: Like, it is not a one time gig.
Chelsea: Right.
Codey: And so investments just, they just hurt.
Codey: I mean, they're, they're larger than a lot of these are and their weaponry is a little stronger.
Codey: Um, not necessarily the venom part of it, but definitely the actual stinging part of it.
Codey: So, um, and I'm not.
Chelsea: That's the thing.
Chelsea: I worry about like being a healthcare person.
Chelsea: I worry about allergies and stuff, like not for me, but I know my next door neighbour has really bad anaphylactic allergy to bee stings.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: So we try to be mindful, but we've never had an issue with any bees at all.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Like they get drunk in our garden.
Chelsea: And they are so cute.
Codey: I mean, you really, like, same with vest beds.
Codey: Like if you, you really have to, to frighten a bee and and mess her up or make her feel like she is in danger.
Codey: Most 9 times out of 10 they're going to fly away.
Codey: They're just like, what the heck?
Codey: And they fly away.
Codey: Um, they'll only sting you if you're either messing with their house and they get scared or if you are trying to mish them.
Codey: Like, I've stepped on a honeybee before because she was, she was nectaring on a clover and I was walking barefoot and I was like, ow.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: And of course, like, that's my own fault.
Codey: My bad.
Chelsea: That was my bad.
Codey: Totally, um, protect yourself, queen.
Codey: But, uh, yeah, so 9 times out of 10, like most people think of the the yellow, like in that yellow and black colouration, it's warning colouration, they're telling you, leave me alone.
Codey: Like they're trying to give every, they're trying to give every indication of don't mess with me.
Chelsea: Yeah, this is for your own safety.
Codey: Um, and so people.
Chelsea: It's like, I'm not stuck in here with you.
Chelsea: You're stuck in here with me.
Codey: The only other type of predatory wasps I wanted to shout out are spider wasps.
Codey: This is the family pompility. And they specialise on eating spiders.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: They will fly and, um, they'll find a spider and they will, um, sting it and immobilise it and then they'll take it back to their nest, still alive, and they will then provision the nest cells because they're solitary. So they will then provision the nest cell that they lay an egg in with a spider that they have immobilised.
Codey: So imagine you're a spider, right?
Codey: You're living your life.
Codey: You're scuttling along.
Codey: You're trying to eat something, whatever.
Codey: And then out of nowhere, someone stabs you.
Codey: You get sleepy, you get abducted.
Codey: And then when you wake up, if you wake up.
Codey: Uh, You are in a closed cell, and a larvae is trying to eat you or is eating you or whatever, because 9 times out of 10, like they're still immobilised by the time they get eaten.
Chelsea: Deputy.
Codey: Um, and some species, some spider families, like there's tarantula hawk wasps are, are in this family.
Codey: So they specialise on tarantulas.
Codey: So this is where you see some really cool battles of a tarantula and a wasp trying to like fight each other.
Codey: Like the tarantula's trying to save herself.
Codey: She's like, leave me alone.
Codey: And, and of course, the spider, the tarantula hawk wasp is like, I'm just trying to feed my babies, dude.
Chelsea: You're not eating me today.
Codey: But it's funny because they're still fairly, they're large for a loss, but they're not usually as big as the tarantula.
Codey: So I'm just imagining them flying back. To their nest with that.
Codey: There's also a loss called the cicada killer wasp, Eastern cicada killer.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: It, one of the largest wasps in our era in where I am geographically, and they immobilise cicadas.
Codey: And then they'll take those back to their nest.
Codey: And I, one time I saw one flying with a cicada and it just, it was cute.
Codey: Like, because it's the wasp times 3 basically, because there's a giant cicada missile flying through the air.
Codey: as well.
Chelsea: Pardon me.
Chelsea: Just gonna go over here.
Codey: And I think she, like, and she, so it was flying in my direction.
Codey: I tried to move out of the way, but she kind of like flew near me, and then she dropped her cicada, and then I was trying, but and it like fell in the flowers.
Chelsea: Oh no.
Codey: And so I tried to pick it.
Codey: I tried to like, I picked it up.
Codey: She, because I watched her.
Codey: she was trying to find it again
Codey: So then I picked it up and put it like a little bit higher and I don't think she ever found it again.
Codey: I'm really sad that she...
Chelsea: Oh, you had such a good catch.
Codey: I was, yeah, I was like, aw, but luckily there's 1000000s of these things right now, so you're fine.
Codey: Just go get another one.
Chelsea: That would be a crazy thing to see, though, like carrying this huge thing.
Codey: Oh my gosh, it was wild.
Codey: Yeah, imagine a cicada, but that being carried by something else.
Codey: And so cicadas are also very clumsy fires, but cicada killer wasps are not.
Codey: It's, it was very,
Chelsea: Oh, okay.
Codey: It was very weird to see, but.
Codey: Okay, last thing we're going to talk about, and then I will be done yapping at y'all about bucks unless you want me to continue yapping.
Codey: You can ask specific things at later episodes or whatever, but I'm not going to be doing it quite the way that I've been doing it.
Codey: Are there beings?
Chelsea: The listeners know what they signed up for.
Codey: They, they do, they do.
Codey: Um, yeah, last thing is the bees. And I did that on purpose because we're going to be talking about bees simulator.
Codey: Um, so the bees, uh, they're in the group, um, Anthophyla, which just means flower loving, and there are seven.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: Yeah, because basically, so bees are basically vegetarian wasps.
Codey: So the majority of wasps and other hemenopterans, or whatever, are either, um, carnivorous and eat other bugs, eat other whatever, um, or they are parasitic.
Codey: But bees are like, nah, nah, dude, I'm going to become a vegetarian, and they rely on flowers, and they have, um, over the last 1000000 years, because about 1000000 years ago that bees 1st show up in the fossil record, what we know of the fossil record.
Codey: Um, B show up and they basically co-evolved with the, with the extreme evolutionary radiation of flowers.
Codey: And it was a, it was an evolutionary arms race that continues to this day, but it's a, it's a co-evolved, like, beneficial one because the flowers were like, wait, you're going to carry my pollen and bees are just trying to either collect the pollen to provision to their young or they're eating the pollen because she needs to produce eggs and she needs the protein from a pollen to do so.
Codey: But they're frequently in interacting with the pollen.
Codey: And because the she, the bees will then go to another flower.
Codey: very effective as a pollinator.
Codey: So, be the, the coevolutionary relationship between bees and flowers is like, just gun gangbusters.
Codey: Um, there would not be nearly as many flower species if there weren't for bees.
Codey: And not just bees.
Codey: I will, I got a pacaveata.
Codey: It's not hashtag not just bees, but bees are the most effective pollinators because of their hair.
Codey: They have branched hairs.
Codey: So instead of their hair, uh, just being like an individual strand, it actually they're, each one is like an individual little feather.
Codey: Um, their pollen collecting hairs are, and it allows the pollen to stick to that area.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Chelsea: Sorry, if I'm being so cute.
Codey: No, you're fine.
Codey: They are very cute.
Codey: Um, because and a lot of them are really fuzzy.
Codey: Not all of them are fuzzy, but a lot like bumblebees are incredibly fuzzy.
Codey: Very cute.
Codey: 90% of bee species are actually solitary.
Codey: So I have to do my my, my work here of uh, battling misinformation.
Codey: Because a lot of folks, when they think of bees, they think of specifically honeybees.
Codey: Um, but honeybee, so the, there are 7 species of honeybee, and only one of those is the honeybee that's in North America, and it's not actually even natives North America.
Codey: It was brought over because people liked honey.
Codey: Um, So whenever I see something that's like, save the bees and it has, uh, like for North America, it's like, save our our bees or whatever, and it has a photo of a honeybee.
Chelsea: Interesting.
Codey: A little bit of me dies.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Those aren't even RB's.
Codey: Not even RB's.
Codey: Um, like not even the ones we need to be saving.
Codey: They're still very important.
Codey: We need to continue to use them.
Codey: They're basically, um, like a, we manage them for their pollination services and for the product, the products that they provide.
Codey: But,
Chelsea: So what is the most important type of beetle?
Codey: So it's, it is a really, it is an, it depends because the way that bees and flowers have coevolved.
Codey: There are going to be bees that are the most effective pollinators for very specific flower species, and vice versa, there's certain flowers that are going to be the most effective source of resources for a bee.
Codey: So it really depends, like if you're trying to say for crop pollination, then it's honestly probably just a not a specific type of bee, but it is to have a strong community of bees in the surrounding area around your crops.
Codey: Um, in if you're growing alfalfa, there is a, the alfalfa leaf cutting bee.
Codey: It is a very specific species of bee that is the most effective pollinator that has co-evolved with alfalfa.
Codey: Um, If you do blueberries and cranberries in the Northeast,
Codey: I'm in the northeast, so I don't know a lot about this. It's a lot of the native bees.
Codey: So the Andronids, the mining bees, I always, I always think of the scientific name and I always have to be like, what is the common name?
Codey: Um, So Andrenity or the mining bees?
Codey: Halictide are the sweat bees, um, Mega Kyli, those are the orchard bees, or and the might, and the, um, Orchard, Mason, Mason bees.
Codey: Um, those are going to be some of the really effective ones.
Codey: And then bumblebees are also incredibly effective depending on where they are, and what they're pollinating.
Chelsea: Mhm.
Codey: Um,
Codey: But yeah, most of them are solitary, so it's going to be a single individual female that mates and then comes in provisions, a nest cell.
Codey: Think of like an ant tunnel.
Codey: Um, so they'll have either underground or in wood.
Codey: They will have a 2 a narrow channel or tunnel that they have excavated or if they use secondary tunnels that they have encountered.
Codey: And then she will, the female will make a provision.
Codey: She'll line the nest to like waterproof it.
Codey: Um, and then she'll provision the nest with food, and then once it's all squared away, she'll lay an egg in that nest and nestle, and then she'll cap it, and then she'll do another one.
Codey: Um, and they do this like a single solitary female could lay up to like 200 eggs, but it's normally a lot less, a lot fewer than that.
Codey: Um,
Codey: And there's so much that I could say.
Codey: But I'm trying to figure out what's most important.
Codey: Yeah, they're just really cool.
Chelsea: Out of curiosity, sorry, were bees what got you into entomology?
Codey: So yes and no.
Codey: So I grew up like playing with all kinds of bugs.
Codey: Like I grew up playing with with praying mantises and with just any bugs that I could get my hands on.
Codey: But as I was finishing my degree in fishers and wildlife at Oregon State University.
Codey: I had done projects on.
Codey: I wanted to save the wolves.
Codey: I wanted to work with wolves, but that is a very contentious thing in Oregon.
Codey: Farmers and ranchers do not necessarily like it.
Codey: When you want to save the thing that is going to eat their cattle.
Codey: Shocking.
Codey: Um, and I am a marshmallow.
Chelsea: Fair enough.
Codey: And so I was like, I can't do that.
Codey: And so I had done a project looking at, um, uh, violet green swallows and tree swallows.
Codey: Um, I, so birds, I had done a project looking at frogs.
Codey: I had done a project looking at, um, using trail cameras to track the movement of deer and elk.
Codey: And then one of the people that I had worked with was like, hey, I want to do this B project, would you be interested in leading it?
Codey: And I was like, hmm, I don't know anything about bees.
Codey: And so that was the first, that was my introduction.
Codey: It was my gateway insect.
Codey: Um, At that time, there was a professor at the university that was teaching a, like, bees of the area, basically class.
Codey: And so I took that and I learned a lot from him.
Codey: It was Dr. Bill Steven.
Codey: I believe he has passed away since then, which is very sad because he was he was a hilarious individual.
Codey: Um,
Codey: And then I led this project for 2 years and I basically identified multiple 1000s of bees in that project.
Codey: And then when I went for my graduate degree, I just stuck with B's because that was what was available.
Codey: I applied to a bunch of different projects, but the one that I got was another B project.
Codey: So I basically did the same thing again.
Codey: And then finally went into true entomology.
Codey: Because my degree at Oregon State was Fisher's of Wildlife and then my degree at my master's institution was just biology.
Codey: Um, but here I got truly entomology.
Codey: Um, and that was actually the 1st time I took like a full entomology course.
Codey: So I didn't even really know about like any of what I've been yapping about for the last 4 episodes.
Codey: I didn't know any of it until like 5 years ago.
Codey: Um, because I had never really taken a bug class, like, except for that one class that was explicitly, here's how you identify bees in this region.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Um, I didn't really know anything.
Chelsea: The gateway bug.
Codey: Gateway bug.
Codey: But then when I was doing when I was studying bees, my mom was very like, well, that makes sense.
Codey: You were playing with bugs all the time as a kid.
Codey: And I think like in hindsight, if I had known that it was a career that I could have.
Codey: Like if Penn State or not Penn State, if Oregon State would have had an entomology programme, I might have jumped to that, but at the time that I was there, the entomology programme had been kind of subsumed into the horticulture programme, because again, because of the how delicately linked.
Chelsea: Oh, okay.
Codey: A lot of bugs are with plants.
Codey: Um, so yeah, I just didn't really have a lot of, um, exposure to the concept of being an entomologist.
Codey: Um, but now Oregon State has a huge B project, like I have what's called the Oregon B Atlas, where they're trying to find all of the B species in Oregon.
Codey: Um, and like beyond as well.
Codey: So it's, I could return, but I don't, I think I think I'll probably end up somewhere else.
Codey: Um, yeah, so they, they kind of were my gateway and so they were the main focus of my research for over a decade.
Chelsea: That's quite the journey.
Codey: Um, and then after that, I was, I just kind of was like, you know, I've been using these traps to catch a lot of bees, but there's a lot more that's than just bees that's caught, they're caught in these traps.
Codey: And so I started taking, I took the fly school, I went to fly school, I went to the coleopter course, and I just gained a love for other things as well.
Codey: So,
Chelsea: That's a crazy journey.
Chelsea: love that.
Codey: It so most entomologists come at it sideways.
Codey: Like, there are very few entomologists that come in, come into college at all being like, I'm going to be an entomologist.
Codey: Um, they usually study, they're like, I'm going to do environmental science, and then while they're doing environmental science, they take a class in entomology, and then they're like, wait a minute, you know, I could do this.
Chelsea: Wait a 2nd.
Chelsea: This is an option.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: And so, um, yeah, it's just something and and also, unfortunately, uh, very underfunded.
Codey: Um, you know, one of the reasons why there is all of this, uh, unsung diversity, unknown diversity, et cetera, et cetera, is because we just don't have the funding or the time or the manpower, uh, with what we currently have, to answer those questions.
Chelsea: Yes, yeah.
Codey: Um, But we should because there's a, there's a lot.
Chelsea: Yes, we should.
Chelsea: It's kind of important.
Codey: So yeah, that was my introduction.
Codey: Bees were my introduction.
Codey: Um, and within B's, my favourite B is uh, a green sweat bee.
Codey: So a lot of the sweat bees.
Codey: They're so-called because they're often attracted to our sweat.
Codey: Like if you are sweaty.
Codey: They, these things, these bees will land on you and they're they're not like the bright yellow, black, crazy colouration.
Codey: They're often a lot smaller than even a honeybee, but they'll land on you and they'll just lick up your sweat.
Chelsea: Like, y'all mind if I just take some?
Codey: It's like, I just, can I have, can I have this?
Codey: Can I have this a little bit?
Chelsea: Can I have this?
Codey: Um, and so that's why they're called that.
Codey: And my favourite bees in this.
Codey: So it's Agacleropsis Metallica.
Codey: Let me go find a photo of it.
Codey: Um, and I actually have a photo or, sorry, a tattoo of this bee because she is just so, um, she, she's a green bee, but she also, in some lights and in some areas, she's more like blue and purple, like a blurpelly colour.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: So I just, she's just so sweet.
Codey: And I just it, it, she bucks convention.
Codey: Like you would think like, oh, you know, green, or you think B, and you think black and yellow, right?
Codey: Or like just a bumblebee, like a big fuzzy thing.
Codey: And she's not fuzzy.
Codey: Um, She, all claps into Elica only have, um, hairs, mostly.
Codey: I mean, they have tiny
Codey: hairs everywhere, but the majority of her hair, her is going to be her pollen collecting hair that she has on her legs.
Codey: Um, I'm putting a link to a photo into the thing.
Codey: There we go.
Codey: Um, and I don't know, it's just one of those green sweat bees are one of the things where if you tell, if you tell someone about bees, then you can show them a picture of this and they're like, I would not have said that was a bee.
Codey: Um, and that, yeah.
Chelsea: I just looked it up, and sorry, we have since Ottawa's cousins of Toronto's unofficial Bee, and there's apparently some book with the start, um, The forward written by Margaret Atwood, whose father was an entomologist.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: I didn't know that.
Chelsea: interesting.
Chelsea: Cool.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: That's crazy.
Codey: Well, I also know, so there was, uh, recently, uh, one of the, like premiere, like, she's, uh, Dr. Sheila Kala recently passed away and she was a Canadian entomologist and she bees were like one of her taxa of interest.
Codey: I think she specifically did bumblebees.
Codey: Um, So you probably, like, if you're looking, if you're looking at bees stuff for Canada, you'll probably come upon her as well.
Codey: She was amazing and she was another like person who was just like, look, this is a bee, like this green thing.
Chelsea: Oh, that's a really cool.
Chelsea: sorry I just saw the photo you posted.
Codey: Yeah, so that's that's them.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: And then, uh, I mean, another.
Chelsea: Subvert expectations.
Codey: Subvert those things, and so another, just looking at this and thinking about green bees, there are other bees that are green, so, and just brightly beautiful colours.
Codey: So the orchid bees are actually in the family apity.
Codey: So the family apity, uh, is where most of what you think of.
Codey: So that's where the honeybees are, that's where the bulblebees are.
Codey: Um, and it's where the, um, My brain or orchid bees.
Codey: See, my brain, I was like, it's you gloss sign bees.
Codey: Like, what is the common name of that?
Codey: Um, so the orchid bees are so named because they, uh, pollinate orchids, um, and the orchids actually, like, mimic the female bee and have a certain like profile that smells like a female bee.
Codey: So then the bee will come in and they'll be like, oh, I'm gonna, like the male bees actually will come in and they think that they're going to mate with a female because that's what they think it is.
Codey: But it's but it's a flower.
Chelsea: Ha, ha. Ha, ha.
Codey: And they fall, they fall into like where the nectary is.
Codey: And, and it's like a, I mean, think of an,
Codey: I mean, if you can't imagine an orchid, like they usually have a chamber, like it's not just a flower.
Codey: Like it's got like a little nectary, like bulb.
Codey: Um, and so the male will fall into that chamber where he'll get a tasty snack.
Codey: There a bunch of a bunch of nectar in there.
Codey: So he's like, what the where the heck am I?
Codey: Oh, this is nice.
Codey: then he'll drink.
Codey: And then the one path in which he can leave will lead him right past a bunch of really sticky pollen.
Codey: And the pollen will get stuck to him, and then he'll squeeze through and he'll leave, and then he'll go get tricked by another orchid, and while he's there, he will sluff off some of the pollen from the previous plant.
Chelsea: Oh my gosh.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: And that is the whole, that's like how or a lot of orchids are pollinated, and that's why these orchid bees are called, um, our exist, and they all are usually also very brightly coloured.
Codey: They're in the tropics.
Codey: And they will also, another interesting thing about them is that they will collect volatiles.
Codey: So floral oils, floral scents, like things that smell a certain, like strong, strong way or whatever, strong strength.
Codey: Um, I mean, in some of them, it's not just that, like, they will collect uh, faeces.
Codey: They will collect urine.
Codey: Like they will basically collect all of these material, this like concoction in their legs.
Codey: There's like a little, like, caldron in the male's legs, and then they will create basically a perfume, and then they will use that to attract a female.
Chelsea: Interesting.
Codey: They are wild.
Codey: Um, they do some of the weirdest things.
Codey: So yeah, I actually saw an orchid bee in Costa Rica as well.
Codey: Um, these things are just nuts.
Codey: Here, I'm going to post a link to a video that's orchid bees.
Codey: Oh, wait, where did it go?
Codey: Orchid bees, brew their own perfume.
Codey: Uh,
Chelsea: So they have their little caldron at the bottom where they make their.
Codey: Yeah, like on their legs, like one of their legs just has like a huge thing, a huge little thing.
Codey: So there's a link to that to just a random ass YouTube video.
Codey: Um, Okay, there's also bumblebees.
Codey: I'm not going to talk about those.
Codey: Another type of bee in the family ABD that I wanted to mention are called nomad bees or nomada is the genus that they're in.
Codey: And these are kleptoparasitic beasts.
Codey: So these are bees that if you look at them, they do not have any, like they're virtually hairless, and they don't even collect pollen, really.
Codey: Um, that's not their their vibe, their vibe.
Codey: is to go into the nests of other bees that are nearly nearly finished.
Codey: So, you know, think, imagine you are a mining bee and you've made a mine and you've provisioned your nest cell and you're young, are totally set up and you're like, okay, this is good.
Codey: And you're like, oh, but I just want to go get one more thing.
Codey: So then you leave the nest, so to go get, um, like some dirt to like close up the cell or whatever.
Codey: These nomad bees or nomad bees will be hovering around in Andrenid's, like, nest site.
Codey: They usually nest in aggregations.
Codey: So the, where a bunch of the andrenas are nesting.
Codey: And when they see a female leave,
Codey: She will go into the nest cell, the tunnel, and she'll find one that's nearly finished, and she'll be like, this is great.
Codey: And she'll lay her egg in it.
Codey: And then their eggs.
Codey: It like a cuckoo.
Codey: They're also called cuckoo bees.
Codey: Um, like a cuckoo bird.
Codey: Their egg will hatch before the mining these egg and that larvae will then eat the mining bee or kill it or something. Uh, different, depending on the species, it's different.
Codey: And then she'll eat the provision.
Codey: And then they'll hatch.
Codey: It won't be a mining bee that hatches.
Codey: It'll be a cuckoo bean.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: They're nuts.
Codey: I just had to mention them.
Codey: Um, because they're just, they're another like, there's always exceptions.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: There's, it's just another version.
Chelsea: Of course.
Codey: Um, and then, yeah, the last thing is honeybees.
Codey: I really don't know what to say about honeybees that people don't already know.
Codey: They do some crazy things.
Codey: dance.
Codey: Um, lot of.
Chelsea: I did the little dance.
Codey: Do a little dancing dance.
Codey: They are really effective pollinators for a lot of crops, um, especially the ones that we grow, that they, we have been using them, but we then have to cart them around North America to be able to use them for pollinators.
Codey: Um, I will say one thing, so a lot of people will say, oh, uh, 40% of the B colonies died or something.
Codey: Like people will talk about huge colony losses.
Codey: Like it's a bad thing.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: And yeah, it's not great.
Codey: But basically a bee, a honeybee colony will overwinter as a cluster.
Codey: So the queen will, it'll be near the winter.
Codey: The queen will lay eggs that will be the winter bees that are a little hardier, the last longer.
Codey: They don't go forage or anything.
Codey: They basically start like clumping around.
Codey: Um, a comb of honey.
Codey: And they just kind of vibrate and they keep themselves warm. And the queen will be in the middle of that. And all winter, they will just be vibrating and just like clumps together.
Codey: They will actually rotate who's on the outside and who's on the inside.
Codey: And over that, over that time.
Codey: Um, the, some of them will die.
Codey: But usually the colony itself will not.
Codey: But if the females were unable to make enough, uh, honey resources or if the beekeeper takes too many, like you are supposed to leave them a certain amount of honey.
Codey: Um, but if you don't, if you don't leave enough, or if they have any of the viruses or mites or like there's a couple, there's a lot of different stressors that can happen.
Codey: Um, the colony itself will not survive to the night to through winter.
Codey: However, people that raise honeybees can actually like, like, duplicate their own nests.
Codey: So if you have, if you had 2 colonies and one of them dies, you can take the existing colony, and after they start building themselves back up again, you can actually separate some of the colony from, or like, remove the queen for a little bit.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: And then they will start being freaked out and they're like, 0 my gosh, where's mom? Because they don't smell mom anymore.
Codey: And they'll create, uh, a queen cell.
Codey: And then, which is a larger cell than normal.
Codey: And then if you reintroduce the queen, she might, she'll lay an egg in there, but and then because the cell is large enough, when the nurse bees start feeding, um, the larvae that is, that is placed into that cell.
Codey: They will continue to feed them what is called royal jelly.
Codey: Um, it's a, it's not just a mixture of honey and pollen.
Codey: It also includes a chemical called Royal Acton that basically, um, continues the development to being a queen instead of just a worker.
Codey: And once you see that your colony has a couple capped queen cells, this is a queen cell that has been capped and a larvae is developing era, pupa is developing inside of it and is going to become an adult.
Codey: You can then take your queen, and a bunch of the workers, and just make a whole other colony.
Codey: And then that queen will emerge from the queen cell, and actually, if a bunch of them emerge at the same time, they will actually fight to the death.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: Yeah, they will fight to the death.
Chelsea: Okay, I was going to say what happens if there's more than one?
Codey: And honestly, so, uh,
Codey: Oh, okay, let me finish what I'm saying.
Codey: Yeah, and then you will have 2 colonies.
Codey: You will have a colony that has new queen and a colony that has the old queen.
Codey: But then you'll just have 2 colonies, period, and you can just keep going from there.
Codey: Um,
Codey: And so it's not uncommon for colonies to not make it.
Codey: So it's whenever people are like, oh, 40% of colony loss.
Codey: I'm like, the expected.
Codey: What's expected?
Codey: Like, It's just how it is.
Chelsea: Just how it is, like.
Codey: It's just it to be that way.
Codey: Um, also, Queens, uh, honeybee colonies will swarm, so that is when they're either their home is threatened or they're grumpy, like they might be overcrowded or whatever, and they will decide to up and leave.
Codey: So they will, um, they'll piece out and they'll either lay, like, it can also happen if they lay queen cells and then the queen will actually abscond, it's called absconding.
Chelsea: No. He's out.
Codey: Um, with a bunch of the workers, like on her own, and people will find these swarms. Um, we actually hilariously passed by one in New York City once.
Codey: And so, and so many people, like, I could tell it was a swarming B colony.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: And bees, bee colonies when they're swarming, they don't have something to defend.
Codey: So unless you like,
Codey: like harm an individual and then she emits alarm for Ramon and then they're all scared.
Codey: Or if you harm the queen, they don't give, they don't care about you at all.
Codey: So they don't like they, and that's why you can see those videos of the, of the girl, like finding a beast swarm and just scooping bees up, like with her hand because they do not care.
Chelsea: No.
Chelsea: Yep, they don't care.
Codey: They don't have a home.
Codey: They're trying to find a home.
Codey: They don't have a home to defend.
Codey: And so there was this huge like clearly a beast swarm and like so many people, there's like a bubble around this swarm because people wanted to like stay away from it or whatever, right?
Codey: I just walked right through it.
Codey: I just walked right there.
Chelsea: Walk right into that.
Codey: Like, they were, they were on, they were swarming on like a flower pot and I just kept going.
Codey: I was like, I have, I got, I got places to be.
Chelsea: They're busy.
Codey: They're not gonna mess with me.
Codey: And I heard people like exclaim.
Codey: And I just like kept, I was, I think I had my headphones in a little bit, but I just like kept going, man, it's fine.
Chelsea: Should have just grabbed one and been like, cool, cool, cool.
Codey: Look at her.
Codey: Yeah, no.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: I was just like, man, I can't I can't be bothered to walk around this.
Codey: Um, so yeah, that's basically that that swarming behaviour is what you are, what honeybee keepers can, um, can leverage to create a new colony.
Chelsea: No.
Codey: Like the colony is already wanting to swarm already like feeling crowded or whatever it is.
Codey: Um, and then you just take them elsewhere and give them another home.
Chelsea: Very cool.
Codey: So, um, a lot of this has to do with B is great uh, setup for B Simulator too.
Chelsea: Yeah, we have.
Codey: Then, yeah, but I mean, we should just then we can just transition into B simulator.
Chelsea: Oh yeah.
Chelsea: Sure.
Chelsea: Before we, before I say that, there's a working farm in Ottawa.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: There's a museum called the Agriculture Museum, and they have a whole B building basically where there's a big glass and you can see the honeycomb being built.
Chelsea: You can spot the queen, you can see the bees going in and out.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: It's so cool.
Chelsea: I go with the kids all the time and they always like, oh, can you find the queens?
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Yeah, pretty easily.
Chelsea: And it's super cool.
Codey: Yeah, I mean, it's, well, and especially, not only, can you usually find her pretty easily because, uh, she, she thick.
Codey: Um, she has a way bigger abdomen than the rest of them, but beekeepers normally uh, routinely will put a dot of paint on her thorax.
Chelsea: Yeah, she had the one in auto.
Chelsea: Yeah, she always has a white, uh...
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So they'll take like a paint pen that you might use, like that you can get from like Home Depot or whatever, and they'll just go bloop right on her thorax.
Chelsea: Hello?
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Um, so then it is incredibly easy to find.
Codey: Um, which is important.
Chelsea: Oh, it's super cool.
Codey: Uh, if you think your colony might be grumpy with her, um, and might be trying to create a new queen.
Codey: Um, because sometimes the calling itself, if her, if for some reason she's getting too old or if they're overcrowded or whatever, and they're unhappy, like they'll start the swarming behaviour, but they might also just kill her.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Okay, that was going to say, if they're really unhappy, well, they just like, Eat her.
Codey: Yeah, they might just kill her.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Um, and then, so that's, so some beekeepers, you always want to have that so that when you go into your colony, you can easily find the queen and you can easily figure out if they have, um, have lost their queen.
Codey: I'm trying to remember the exact terminology.
Codey: Part of me wants to say that it's Queen wrong or Queen wrong.
Codey: Yeah, Queen Wrong versus Queen Wright.
Codey: But, um, yeah.
Codey: So. Woo, that's my rant.
Codey: About bugs. Um,
Chelsea: So people wanted.
Chelsea: So the game we're talking about today is B Simulator.
Chelsea: Um, I played on PC.
Chelsea: How did you play?
Codey: Uh Xbox.
Chelsea: Xbox.
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: So I, yeah, I used Xbox controller.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Uh, so basically, you live the lifecycle of a B.
Chelsea: Um, you can pick your own name or you can use your name that is suggested to you, uh, which is Biscuit, which is amazing. I kept, I kept mine too.
Codey: Okay, I kept, I just went with beast good.
Chelsea: I kept mine too.
Chelsea: So, you basically do the tasks of a bee.
Chelsea: So the options throughout your day are collect.
Chelsea: So you fly through hoops to collect pollen from flowers, and there are different rarities of flowers that have different categories of pollen.
Chelsea: Um, there's race, which is fly through hoops basically and try to, you know, beat an enemy fight, which I have questions about.
Codey: Okay.
Chelsea: Um, so basically you would defend yourself, uh, by stinging, which I don't think you're doing, to be quite honest in real life.
Codey: Yeah, not really.
Chelsea: No, um, dance.
Chelsea: So basically, you come across another bee and either they're lost or you're lost and you have to mimic the directions that they give you.
Chelsea: Uh, which I thought was cute.
Codey: Also, also not true though.
Chelsea: Okay.
Chelsea: Sting, which you can do on people, balloons, different things in the environment, just if you want to wreak havoc in Central Park.
Chelsea: You are encouraged to do that.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: Um, and then standard missions.
Chelsea: So basically helping other bees in the hive, helping animals find their lost mom, which, okay.
Chelsea: Um, and basically, uh, you learn from the start, oh, humans are evil, humans are evil.
Chelsea: Um, they're trying to destroy our hive, so the tree that your hive is in gets cut down.
Chelsea: Um, so then you go to look for another hive even though you're a honeybee, you're not supposed to, you're not, that's not your job.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: But you still find a home.
Chelsea: Um, and then, as you get towards the end, I don't know, I think this happens for everybody.
Chelsea: But you basically pass out and then a human feeds you a sugar cube and teaches you like how to care for bees if you see them in distress, that kind of thing.
Chelsea: Um, and yeah, so basically the story for me, took about 4 to 5 hours.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um, is that kind of the same for you? Or a little less.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: Yeah, I didn't do everything.
Chelsea: So I still have, I got to credits.
Chelsea: But I still have a lot of things left to do.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: Um, things I didn't even think about, like, uh, change the radio with your stinger.
Chelsea: Um,
Codey: Yeah, nope, not gonna do that.
Chelsea: No, but meanwhile, um, while you're going around as a bee, you can turn into bee vision, which is basically I want to say, not infrared, but, I don't know if bees actually do this, but like this these things inverted almost in colour.
Chelsea: Um, is that kind of,
Codey: Uh, so it, they, it's not something they can turn off or turn on.
Codey: They basically, uh, bees have a different spectra that they can see, and they can actually see ultraviolet.
Chelsea: No, no.
Codey: So, um, when they look at a flower, for example, there are usually lines that we can't see in the flower that kind of direct the bee wear on the flower to go.
Codey: Um, and depending on the bees, like they might like certain, they might prefer certain flower colours, um, whatever.
Codey: Uh, it will almost always not be a red flower.
Codey: But there is a, there is some truth to some resources being better than others.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, because they have it categorised as like epic pollen.
Codey: Yeah, there will be some pollen that is, and there's actually a whole like study of of bees where, um, people are looking at the nutritional capability of different flowers and how different bee species need specific pollen nectar ratios.
Chelsea: Um.
Codey: Um, or and sorry, not pollinectar, uh, protein lipid.
Chelsea: Oh, interesting.
Codey: Oh my goodness.
Codey: So the ratio of protein to fat, that either the pollen or the nectar might provide, and that certain species of bee might prefer certain flowers, because it has a ratio that is closer to what they need.
Chelsea: Oh, interesting.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um, yeah, that was not really mentioned.
Chelsea: In the game.
Codey: No, there's there's I will get to my critique.
Chelsea: Yes, okay.
Codey: But I'll let you keep excited.
Chelsea: Um, sure.
Chelsea: So you can go around, like once you beat the story, you can kind of just free Rome as you want.
Chelsea: And I think even without the main story.
Chelsea: You still can.
Chelsea: I just wanted to get to the credits to see what the end was.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: But you can come across different wildlife and you can record them with knowledge points in your hive.
Chelsea: You have this little archive library where you can make a little, um, nature journal, I want to say, where you make these little trophies of, you know, an ants or a deer and like all these different creatures that you come across.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um, and then you can ask them for advice throughout the game.
Chelsea: But, um, and with the loading screens and stuff.
Chelsea: It gives facts that, you know, you may not know and resources to help your your local bee community.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Um, I bought it on sale.
Chelsea: Um, this game's from 2019 and it's still being sold at $55 Canadian, full price.
Chelsea: Um, I don't know how I feel about that.
Chelsea: Um, if you really want to play it, though, I guess, you know, you'll play what you want, but uh, I don't think it's a really long game from what I've seen, even if you want to 100% completed.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: I've seen people say it takes about 10 hours to unlock everything to get the 100% achievement.
Chelsea: Um, yeah, so what are your thoughts?
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: What are your, uh, accurate nature thoughts about this?
Codey: Okay.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: I'm gonna go down the list.
Codey: Okay, so.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: So be life cycle.
Codey: You wake up and pick a name and then they're immediately like, get to foraging.
Codey: Uh, wrong.
Codey: So, be, honeybees, when they emerge from their nest cell, uh, they are and they are immediately become nurse bees.
Chelsea: Wrong.
Codey: So they immediately begin taking care of the bees that were there that are right there as well.
Codey: Um,
Codey: They might also do have like nest cleaning or like, yeah, hive cleaning duties.
Codey: So there are some that are kind of like the janitors of the nest.
Codey: Um, so if like a bee died in it or if they find something that is, um, bad, like something, uh, just some type of debris or something, they will remove those, they, if they find a tear in the hive, they'll fix that with wax.
Codey: Um, uh, or propolis is another thing that they use for that.
Codey: Um, but it isn't until they're like a week or 2 old that they will switch to becoming foragers.
Codey: So the waking up and immediately being a forager is not correct.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: Um,
Codey: But otherwise, I mean, the foraging part seemed fine to me, going out and bringing stuff back.
Codey: Um, the, um, collecting.
Codey: I mean, you just fly, fly and we just, yeah, I mean, it's that's pretty standard.
Chelsea: Yeah, they have checkpoints where it's like, oh, my legs are dripping with pollen.
Chelsea: I need to drop this off at the honeycomb.
Codey: Yeah, um, the race, I mean, be probably don't race each other in the wild.
Codey: I don't know, though.
Chelsea: No, well, no, no.
Codey: We don't know that.
Chelsea: I don't know that.
Codey: I I don't know that.
Codey: Okay, the fight.
Codey: So this is not accurate either.
Codey: Like, if an individual bee were to start fighting a wasp, like, she's going to fly away.
Codey: She's not she's not going to try and do that.
Codey: Um, and it was usually yellow jackets specifically, which don't really mess with bees.
Codey: So, with, specifically, honey.
Chelsea: No, and they were all French for some reason.
Codey: They were all French.
Codey: They were all like really mean, like they were just so mean and so I didn't, I didn't appreciate that.
Codey: Because for the most part, they're not going to be messing.
Codey: There are some wasps that, uh, and I'm trying to remember, I think they are in the family vet.
Codey: I know there are some in the family Vespity, but there might be some in the family's Fekity as well.
Codey: that, um, will attack honeybee hives.
Codey: Like, think of the murder hornet.
Codey: Um, that is a Vespid, uh, wasp that will come and kill a bunch of honeybees and will either eat them or use them to provision her nest.
Codey: I'm not, I don't really understand that they're, um, not in the North America, but a few individuals were found in North America and everyone thought that they were going to take over, um, and they're going to be here.
Codey: Did you not hear about this at all?
Codey: Okay, I was like, wait, you.
Chelsea: Yeah, I, I, I, I kind of suppressed it a little bit.
Codey: You said, oh, wow.
Chelsea: Yeah, no, it's it's talking about memory.
Codey: And I was like, excuse me.
Chelsea: Hold on.
Codey: Because this is huge.
Chelsea: No, I remember, I think I suppressed it a little bit.
Codey: Well, because it was also, it was a 2020 thing as well.
Codey: So then we were all at home and we were all.
Chelsea: Put the hornets back.
Codey: Yeah, and people were like, murder hornet, like this this year can't get any worse.
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: Surprise.
Codey: But and and when bees do fight against something like that.
Codey: what they do is they actually, and like you, I guess you kind of do this at one point, like the wasps come to your hive and you kind of dogpile onto them.
Codey: So that's what they do.
Codey: Um, uh, honeybees will jump on top of the whatever the wasp, whatever whatever wasp or whatever it is.
Codey: And they kind of dogpile onto it.
Codey: So then you don't see the wasp anymore.
Codey: You just see a writhing mass of bees.
Codey: And they then vibrate their thoracic muscles and their wing muscles and that generates heat and they basically cook the wasp.
Codey: And that is how they fight.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Wow.
Chelsea: So yeah, you're not meeting them alone.
Codey: So, That could have been really cool. That could have been really cool.
Chelsea: Like, you're not doing a one-to-one.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Um.
Chelsea: Yeah, no, because, um,
Chelsea: This is kind of a silly question probably, but do bees know that if they sting that they're done.
Codey: I don't necessarily know if we, I don't think.
Chelsea: I don't know why I'm asking you like.
Codey: No, no, it's fine.
Codey: I don't, I don't know if they know, like, we don't really have a way to understand that.
Chelsea: Can you communicate with these?
Codey: But the other thing is that so.
Codey: Uh, so yeah, honeybee females, when they, so males, male, anything, male wasps don't have, uh, a stinger, because the stinger is a modify ovipositor, and the ovipositor is an egg laying organ, which is a female thing, males have penises instead, period.
Codey: And so if it's a male, it's not going to be able to sting.
Codey: any that are going to possibly sting you is going to be female.
Codey: Um,
Codey: And the barbed nature of the honeybee stinger is effective, uh, at like the, it will actually stick in the skin of pretty much specifically a mammal.
Codey: Um, and we think that it evolved because of bears.
Codey: Um, and so, like, if a bee stays another insect, it will break the cuticle, but it won't stick in the same way that it does human skin.
Chelsea: Interesting.
Codey: So they could repeatedly sting a wasp like that.
Codey: And when like queens are fighting, for example, um, like if there are more than one queen in a hive, um, or if the colony is mad at their queen and they want to kill her, they stinger, they stinger, they bite her, like whatever.
Codey: Like it's just another weapon.
Codey: Um,
Codey: But it's not something that it's not their 1st line of attack.
Codey: not like the way that it is in the game.
Codey: Um,
Chelsea: No, you're like, hit them with your stinger right now.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Uh, I mean, it's a it's a rhythm game.
Codey: It's interesting, but yeah, it's not quite the same.
Codey: Um, The dance?
Codey: Okay, so the waggle dance that bees do is on the comb.
Codey: So the dance that you do in the game is in midair with another individual B.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: And basically, uh, when a bee does a waggle dance.
Codey: She comes back to her hive.
Codey: She has found a resource and they do this not only for, um, for food, but also if they're swarming.
Codey: So they will actually go searching for a new home.
Codey: This is something that bees will actually do when they're swarming.
Codey: Um, and they will do another similar dance to, um, to communicate to the other bees about the quality of their home.
Codey: So the waggle dance has 3 components.
Codey: It conveys direction, it conveys, distance, and it conveys quality.
Codey: So they basically move in a figure 8 motion.
Codey: And the amount of time that she spends doing the, the actually, she's like moving her butt back and forth and she's waggling in a straight line.
Codey: That is conveying distance, the actual, how she is oriented, like think of a clock.
Codey: If she's oriented at 3 o'clock on the frame or 6 o'clock on the frame or whatever, that is how she's telling uh, the orientation, like what actual direction to go to.
Codey: Um, and I think that I don't 100% know, but it has to do with the sun.
Codey: Like she's basically saying this direction from the sun.
Codey: Like this much of an angle from the sun.
Codey: Uh, go that direction for this amount of time, for this, this long.
Codey: And then how quickly she returns to the front of the dance conveys, um, quality.
Codey: It's nuts.
Chelsea: Wow, that's incredible.
Codey: It's absolutely nuts.
Codey: And so if you see, to be side by side. And one, um, you know, she waggles her her straight line portion is fairly short.
Codey: So you're like, okay, cool, pretty close by, right?
Codey: Um, And she's oriented, I guess the the actual direction doesn't really matter.
Codey: But then her return journey is kind of slow.
Codey: So she's basically saying, it's an okay resource, but it's pretty close by.
Codey: But then you see like Martha down the down the comb and she is just a speed demon and even like even though her straight portion is pretty long, so it's probably fairly far away, she is excited about that thing, like, 0 my goodness.
Codey: And then they will actually do the waggle dance before they deposit, they regurgitate from their honeys, the nectar from their honey stomach.
Codey: And so other females will come up to her.
Codey: She'll be like, Martha, like what?
Codey: What are you talking about?
Codey: And she'll they'll basically, she'll regurgitate some as like, um, a taste.
Codey: She's like, here's a sample.
Chelsea: Try this.
Codey: Try it.
Codey: And then, you know, if whoever, whatever B is the most convincing, um, is the resource that they go is like the where what resources they're going to go with.
Codey: And then when that female gets back, she will convey the information again, and they just do that over, like they're constantly doing that.
Codey: Honeybee hives have like 10s of 1000s of individuals.
Codey: So on any amount of comb, like any comb that is the honeycomb part of their, um, the structure that they've created, it, this is happening, like dozens of times because they will all go out en masse and find resources and come back and and communicate how how good the resources or whatever.
Chelsea: Girl, you'll never believe what I just found.
Codey: Girl?
Codey: Or like, it's okay.
Codey: I mean, if we have nothing else to choose from, like we could do this.
Codey: Um...
Chelsea: Right.
Chelsea: Yeah, the dance the dancing in the game was like, here's where your mom is.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: I'm gonna show you this dance and like, obviously it's a, you know what I mean?
Chelsea: It's not a simulator.
Codey: It's like a rhythm game, yeah.
Chelsea: RPG.
Chelsea: I'd say.
Chelsea: Yeah, and it's cute.
Codey: As well.
Chelsea: Yeah, but midair, like you're not going to see that.
Codey: But.
Codey: Yeah, you're not gonna see it quite like that.
Codey: Um, Sting.
Codey: Okay, so a straightforward bully singing.
Codey: So they're basically, you sting people for fun wouldn't happen because again, if you sting a mammal, that stinger coming out.
Chelsea: Yep.
Chelsea: So.
Codey: And not only does the stinger come out, but usually, so there's also the venom gland comes out.
Codey: So attached to honeybee stingers, there's a venom gland that is constantly producing venom, and then attached to that is also a muscle that when the stinger is activated, and the venom is activated.
Codey: The muscle will pump venom, and will basically continue to pump venom.
Codey: And there's an also a gland that emits alarm pheromone.
Codey: And so basically, you know, the queen, or not the queen, the female stings you, she gets brushed off, falls off, whatever, and she's like 5 feet away, right?
Codey: But the beacon that is telling all of the other females,
Codey: This is the problem is still in you.
Codey: It's still in your skin.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: So the 1st thing to do is to get that out and move away because they will, they use that pheromone, that alarm pheromone to basically, it's like all hands on deck.
Codey: We need to, this is a problem, and we need to fight it, and as long as you smell like that, you're gonna get bees.
Codey: As long as you're in the area of the colony, you're going to continue to get attacked.
Codey: So you need to move away.
Codey: That's why like water might be good.
Codey: It's also why beekeepers use smoke because the smoke masks the pheromones.
Chelsea: Yep.
Codey: So even if some of them are like our omitting alarm pheromone, then it like dulls it on top of, if you put smoke in the air, when they're breathing, it kind of like, I mean, if you've ever walked through a cloud of smoke, you know.
Codey: Um, like you just, you kind of get distracted by, uh, breathing.
Codey: rather than whatever might be hurting you in the area.
Chelsea: Right.
Codey: And then once you leave, they're fine.
Codey: But um, yeah.
Codey: So stinging is not necessarily something they're gonna, it's not, no, not that way.
Chelsea: I figured it was just for fun because you can, one of the achievements is pop all the balloons.
Codey: Yeah, no.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: It's like, oh, just something to do.
Codey: I mean, that's cute.
Codey: I don't know if I don't know what they would do with a balloon.
Codey: Um, yeah, this place is this place is basically Central Park.
Codey: And your hive, your initial hive is in a tree in the elk exhibit of the Central Park Zoo is what seems like is happening.
Chelsea: Yep.
Codey: And it the tree that you have.
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: It looks like a really old ratchety tree.
Codey: So I think the humans are just trying to get rid of it, like to chop it down because it's just an old ass tree.
Codey: Like that tree's...
Chelsea: Yeah, I wouldn't say there's any like, it's not like the evil humans are deforesting.
Chelsea: It's like, no, this tree is going to kill all the elk in this exhibit, if it falls.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Yeah, this tree is going to fall on one of these elk and it's going that elk is going to get killed because this is a giant old tree.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Um, I mean, and it could also be that, like, they see that there's a beehive in there and they're like, wait a minute, like, like, we don't want this.
Codey: This is a zoo, right?
Codey: I don't necessarily think it's that.
Codey: I think it's more likely that it's the, that this is a dead ass tree.
Codey: Um, You can't understand what they're saying.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: Like if you go up to any of the people to sting them or whatever, it's like garble, like there's no, you can't tell what they're saying.
Chelsea: It's kind of funny.
Chelsea: Yeah, it's like the, Charlie Brown, like, wa, wa, wa, wa, like no clue what's happening.
Codey: Wah, wah, wah, yeah.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: I thought that was a neat touch.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: So I guess that's my.
Codey: Oh, I, one more uh, nit to pick.
Codey: Um, I, when I started playing this, I immediately took, um, a note.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: I just got to scroll back through.
Codey: Um, okay.
Codey: The one of the very 1st thing.
Codey: So whenever you start a new game, it goes over like how important honeybees are, how important pollinators are, da da da da.
Codey: And one of the things they say verbatim is honeybees are the most important pollinators, and I was triggered by that.
Chelsea: You're like, hmm, actually.
Codey: No, actually, like it, the, what is the most important pollinator is an it depends on what is being pollinated?
Codey: Um, something like alfal.
Chelsea: That's such a vague term.
Codey: It's so vague.
Codey: Like something like alfalfa.
Codey: But honeybees cannot pollinate it, period, because the pollen is like spring loaded, and then they don't really catch it.
Codey: So they just get their bootees handed to them whenever they try and pollinate alfalfa.
Codey: There's a whole other beef for that, my guy.
Codey: like don't even.
Codey: So people don't use, they, they will use alfalfa mining bees for, or, or, mason bees for that.
Codey: Um, so yeah, it really, the whole like honeybees are the most important pollinators.
Codey: Mm, no.
Codey: And especially because it seems like it's Central Park.
Codey: If you're talking about North America,
Codey: The majority of the flowers in this area have not coevolved with honeybees, they've coevolved with other bees.
Codey: And another thing is that honeybees, um, because they collect a resource.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: They will monopolise a resource, and if there are other bees trying to use that resource.
Codey: They will actively, like, dissuade other, like, like dissuade other bees from using the resource.
Codey: Um, and also just make it so that other bees can't use the resource because they've used it all, right?
Codey: And so honeybees might actually, there's still, the jury's still out, but a lot of entomologists, myself included, think that honeybees will have a negative impact on native North American bees because of the way that they go and eat everything.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: So then they just they just hoard them all.
Chelsea: They just hoard all the resources.
Codey: Um, So the the statement honeybees are the most important pollinators.
Codey: I got to refute it.
Codey: No.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: Like, I give, like, I know they're trying to, you know, raise awareness and I feel like this game would be more meant for children. Like, as a science like project, maybe like, oh, let's let's learn about bees and stuff.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: But yeah, I like, Pretty easy to get these facts correct, I think.
Codey: I do also think there are ways that they could have still used the same, like they could have had the dance thing, but still have it be true.
Codey: Like, still have, like, just do the waggle dance, my guy.
Codey: Like just, just do it.
Chelsea: Still a bit?
Codey: Um, Or like fight, only have the fight happen when it's wasps trying to get into your hive and you go and jump on, jump on the wasp with your sisters and cook it.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: One thing for me that.
Codey: Like.
Chelsea: Yeah, I wish, yeah, because they they show a cut scene of you vibrating through the through the winter.
Chelsea: Like, you're all cuddling together.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: That's one of the cutscenes for like, and then then we were quiet through the winter and then it warmed up and all that stuff, which was nice.
Chelsea: But yeah, then you have like this French angry wasp out of nowhere, attacking you.
Codey: Why France?
Chelsea: And I'm like, what is happening?
Codey: Like France, France is, France is catching strays here.
Chelsea: And it's,
Chelsea: And it's all the same person.
Chelsea: It's so funny.
Codey: It is.
Chelsea: Like, I wish I could just play a clip, but you're like, me.
Codey: It's like the, the one voice, like she'll talk normally, but then 1st another bee, she might just like have a little bit of a high voice and then she'll talk, and then it's, and then when it's the wasp, it's just, it's just angry and me, and it's like,
Chelsea: Yeah, the babies have the higher.
Chelsea: Angry and oh, frosted.
Chelsea: Like, wow, okay.
Chelsea: No, and then, okay, so the scene where you have to find the new hive and your hive is collapsing and you're going to go get all the baby larvae.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: So is that kind of all hands on deck for that kind of thing or are there designated bees to do that?
Codey: Um.
Codey: I, I don't, I don't think they take the babies.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, I was like, are you sure they're taking all these like little baby larvae?
Codey: So, Ants definitely do that.
Codey: Like an ant will definitely, like they, because their, their larvae are just in, in a tunnel and they can just grab them.
Codey: Honeybee larvae are in like a hole that you would then they would then have to like pull them out of.
Codey: And I just don't.
Chelsea: That was my question too.
Chelsea: was like, are they in like a encasement?
Codey: Yeah, so honey, all honeybee, larvae, they basically, like, think of honeycomb.
Chelsea: And you have the...
Codey: They're just in that.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: I mean, they just put them, they just, so there's usually in a, in a honeybee hive, like the kinds that we have.
Codey: There's usually what is known as a frame that is the honey, like they'll, they'll have a couple that are honey frames that are all, will all have honey.
Codey: But then they will have a few healthy colonies will have a few, um, larval frames as well.
Codey: So it's an entire frame that is like the same size as a honey frame, but it's full of babies.
Codey: Um, and I don't, I really don't think they take them.
Chelsea: So I was going to say, if a hybrid to collapse, are they just trying to like, That's kind of collateral damage.
Codey: They just bail.
Codey: Because it's, I mean, it's not, it's not worth it.
Codey: Like if you don't have a home in which to put that female, that larva to then raise it, because you won't even have resources to provide that larva, because all the resources are in the home that you just left.
Chelsea: No.
Chelsea: That's it.
Codey: So you wouldn't, they wouldn't do that at all.
Codey: It would just.
Chelsea: Well, that's like what I texted you last night.
Chelsea: I'm like, so what mental illness is it that I'm crying a beast simulator over these larvae?
Chelsea: And you're like, oh.
Chelsea: I figured, like, it's like, not a kind of a fetch quest, like, oh, save the babies.
Codey: Yeah, and it was.
Chelsea: But I'm like, they probably don't do that in real life.
Chelsea: They probably just save, you know, like majority rules, get out of there if you can.
Codey: No, I think.
Chelsea: Self preservation.
Codey: So something that does happen that I want to do a greenhouse on this, something that does happen, um, is the males.
Codey: So we've mostly been talking about females because the majority of them are females, but the colony will create males, like the female, sorry, the colony will develop drone cells, which are larger than a regular cell.
Codey: And the queen will tell can tell that it's larger.
Codey: She measures whenever that she's laying an egg.
Codey: She measures it with her antenna.
Codey: And depending on the size, she will lay either a fertilised egg, which becomes a female or an unfertilised egg, which becomes a male.
Codey: And if it, if a, uh, once the males hatch in our, they basically just like, are free loaders in the hive, like they will just eat the honey.
Codey: And then during the day, they like heck off to go to an area that's called a congregation zone area where they, all the males of all the neighbouring hives, just kind of chill and like fly around in a circle until...
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Chelsea: Every species of my.
Codey: Until, Until like freshly emerged queens that are unmated will fly and they'll find these drone congregation areas and they will then mate with an average of 12 males and they will save all of the sperm in a specialised organ they have called the spermatheca.
Chelsea: I'm kidding, don't cancel me.
Chelsea: No, cancel me.
Codey: Um, and then she will then use all of that sperm that she has, that she has gotten to create all of the workers that she ever, like she only ever has to do that flight wants.
Codey: She never has to leave the hive once she's mated.
Codey: But if you're a male, and you somehow, and the males die, the males just die after they mate.
Chelsea: Wow.
Codey: But if you're a male and you you survive to winter, There is a day where the females, the workers are just like, uh, you're done.
Codey: And they will root out all of the males in the hive and bite them and sting them and run them out of the hive and chew off their wings.
Codey: And if the males try and get back into the hive, they just kick him out again, like they are at their ready at the gate, like you are not getting back in.
Chelsea: Oh my gosh.
Codey: And, There is an amazing book, um, called The Life of a Bee that I found, uh, a copy of that is, it was written in like the early 1900s and there was an entire chapter.
Chelsea: Stay out of our sisterhood.
Codey: Well, the whole book is like a flowery way, like the way that the author writes is very flowery describing things and he has an entire chapter called the massacre of the males that describes this whole process.
Codey: And I, for a greenhouse, I just want to read this, like read this chapter. So we don't have to do it today, but like, because we've been recording for how many.
Chelsea: Okay, let's do it.
Chelsea: I'm I need.
Codey: But like, I want to do it because, and that would, that would be another thing that would have been so fun.
Chelsea: Yes.
Codey: Like that could have been the fetch quest.
Codey: It's like, okay, we need to leave.
Codey: But on top of that, we yeah, we don't need these men.
Chelsea: Let's kill all the men.
Codey: Like, these men are going to try and follow us and they're just going to use resources.
Codey: We're trying to rebuild and they're just like eating and not providing anything.
Codey: We don't need them right now.
Chelsea: Mooching off the ladies.
Codey: Let's just go kill the men.
Codey: Um, and I know like that's...
Chelsea: Can you imagine that in Bee Simulator?
Codey: I literally, I literally was just like, let's go kill the men and I was like, well, that's probably the episode.
Chelsea: And then you get a little like, you get like a little steam.
Codey: That's the episode title.
Codey: And then also like...
Chelsea: You get a little steam achievement pop up.
Codey: Someone's gonna, like, snap this out of, like, clip this out of context and be like, Cody thinks men should die.
Chelsea: Oh.
Chelsea: No, no, no, no.
Codey: But yeah, I think that would have been a great alternative fetch quest instead of, um,
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Chelsea: That should be, um, the finale of Bug Month for that greenhouse is just read that book.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: We should do it.
Codey: Well, I don't know about that.
Codey: I haven't read the whole book, but definitely at least that chapter.
Codey: Um, I feel like because also just the way he writes.
Codey: I'm like, why don't we write this way anymore?
Codey: Like now we're talking about, you know, she uses her antenna to measure the diameter of the da da da.
Codey: Like he probably would have said something like, the queen, um, assesses the the quality of the nest cell.
Codey: And if it behoves her one way, chalet a drone.
Codey: And if it, if she, if it catches her in another way.
Codey: And like he is just very flowery, very like, We just don't write like that anymore and part of me thinks we should.
Chelsea: No.
Codey: Because I would I need to read that book front to back.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: I always just read the one chapter.
Chelsea: I was always like, I'm wondering if the next chapter just goes back to normal and like it's never mentioned again.
Codey: Maybe, maybe we should, maybe like for that greenhouse, I'll read the preceding chapter and then that chapter and then the following chapter.
Chelsea: Oh, I see it here.
Chelsea: The life of the B, Nobel Prize in literature.
Chelsea: That one or the one by Maurice Maeterlink.
Codey: Maurice Vaderling is what it is.
Chelsea: There's a...
Chelsea: Yeah.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, okay.
Chelsea: Yep.
Chelsea: I'm going to see if my library has it because I am very curious.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: You should, dude.
Codey: I love that, but.
Chelsea: Anyway, if you want to have a cute romanticised idea of how a bee survives.
Codey: Uh, yeah.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: This is a nice fun game for you.
Codey: I still think it's it's like a fun, cute little game.
Chelsea: It's cute.
Codey: I do think it like, it also, um, although it has some factual inaccuracies.
Codey: It is still, it still paints bees in a really positive light.
Codey: Um, so it'll still possibly like endear some people who might be against bugs, 2 bugs.
Codey: So I'm always here for that.
Codey: Um, yeah.
Codey: So I still would recommend it.
Codey: I would probably recommend it for a younger audience and definitely do not pay 55 Canadian for it.
Chelsea: No, please don't.
Chelsea: Please don't.
Codey: You got it on sale.
Chelsea: It's on steam sale right now.
Chelsea: Yeah, I got it for, I think, 1999.
Codey: Um.
Chelsea: But I'll probably go back and finish the, just see what some of the achievements are and get my money's worth.
Codey: Oh, it's currently, you currently save 80%.
Codey: It is $4.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: So it's normally $20 USD.
Chelsea: Come on.
Codey: Our currencies are not that different, are they?
Chelsea: Uh.
Codey: No, they're not.
Codey: Yeah, it's cur and it's $27 Canadian on Steam here.
Chelsea: That's okay, because on Switch, it's 15.
Codey: Yeah, no, it's that's how much it is.
Codey: And then it's currently $4, uh, which is 558 Canadian and then, you know what?
Codey: Just for gigs.
Codey: Let's do the Euro.
Codey: Uh, 3
Codey: Oh, wow, the dollar sucks.
Codey: 350.
Codey: Uh, it is 350, 3.5 euros right now on Steam, at least.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: But yeah, that, oh, there's an art book.
Codey: Oh yeah, there's the hive bundle.
Chelsea: Oh, the DLC where you can customise your own honeycomb.
Chelsea: I think is what it is.
Codey: Oh, it says literally says a world inspired by Central Park.
Codey: Get out of here.
Codey: Introducing new mechanics game modes and fresh as spring pollen content.
Chelsea: You ever?
Codey: Interesting.
Chelsea: Uh.
Codey: Yeah, I'm not going to do it.
Codey: But um...
Chelsea: That's great for someone else.
Codey: Great.
Codey: It's great for someone else.
Codey: I am curious what they added, but not enough to play it again.
Codey: I mean, and it's so it's also on game pass.
Codey: which is how I played it.
Codey: So I didn't pay anything for it.
Chelsea: Okay.
Codey: So it's one of those, like, if you have Game Pass, it's worth looking at.
Codey: I mean, it's only like, like you said, and I similarly got to credits in like 4 hours.
Codey: So it's not going to take your time.
Chelsea: Yeah.
Codey: It's not going to take that much time away from you.
Codey: So worth worth exploring.
Codey: Um, but definitely, definitely uh, ruffled some of my feathers a little bit.
Chelsea: Yeah, you.
Chelsea: Yeah, it's a good gateway into maybe being more interested in bugs, but uh...
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Codey: Yeah, if you want to play a honeybee game, I recommend Apico.
Codey: So that is we've covered Apico on the podcast before.
Codey: It's a game in which you are a beekeeper, but you are using your powers for good.
Codey: And you, um...
Codey: I don't know if you know.
Chelsea: Or is the wording of that?
Codey: I don't know if you know the story or not.
Codey: So, uh, it's the developers from uh, Europe and in Europe, honeybees are native, so I will reduce some of my ire.
Codey: But, um, all of the bees that you that are in Apico and the base Ipico are honeybees, basically.
Codey: But you're trying to find, um, the different species, like subspeed, and there's like a water one and a pond one, like there, it's not like a certain species.
Codey: It's like variants, basically.
Codey: And you are trying to find them, collect them, and then return, like, like basically build them up and return them to the world.
Codey: So it's it's nice.
Codey: They also, I think, 10% of the proceeds go to supporting, um, uh, be, or uh, insect consteration.
Chelsea: Oh, interesting.
Chelsea: Oh, good.
Chelsea: See, I'm hoping be simulated to something like that.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: I don't I don't know.
Chelsea: But I don't, I don't see anything like off the top because I feel like if it did, it would be plastered everywhere.
Codey: I don't think they do.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Um,
Codey: Um, but Apico, so when we covered Apico on the pod, um, we were talking to developer L, I had to go on my rant a little bit about how honeybees aren't the only bees, da da da.
Codey: So Ell ended up, they ended up developing a DLC in which solitary bees are introduced and butterflies. And the solitary bee scientist that like, she's based on me.
Codey: And she, yeah, she basically like comes to your island and she's like, let me see your book and you show her your journal and she's like, you don't know anything and she like, tears out pages and adds a bunch of pages and she's like, go learn about solitary bees.
Chelsea: Oh my god!
Codey: And I'm like, honestly, that's, Kind of how I feel I come across sometimes.
Chelsea: That's incredible.
Codey: So, um, but yeah, it's, it's, It was just really funny that I basically, like, we interviewed them and then I, I can't remember if it was before the interview.
Chelsea: That's hilarious.
Chelsea: amazing.
Chelsea: Okay, I need to go play that.
Codey: I think it was after the interview, like I was like, let me know if you want to hear about solitary beasts.
Chelsea: That's incredible.
Codey: And then they like bounced a couple things off of me a couple times.
Codey: Like, oh, how about this?
Codey: What do you think of this?
Codey: And I was like, yeah, sure.
Codey: And then they were like, here's your Sprite.
Codey: Like, or give me a photo that can be your Sprite.
Chelsea: This is you.
Codey: And I was like, okay, here's a photo of me in overalls.
Codey: And then that's what my character is wearing.
Chelsea: Oh my god, okay, I need to look at that immediately.
Codey: Um, yeah, it was, so that's, if you want to play a game about honeybees, I, I'm a little biased, but also, I think it's a game that's actually, like, part of the proceeds go to support conservation, it covers, um, solitary bees and butterflies as well.
Codey: And the butterfly scientist is also based on a real scientist.
Codey: And I think, um, it's not, it's canon that, uh, so they're, we're both female scientists, pat scientists and it's cannets that candid.
Chelsea: So cool.
Codey: Oh my gosh, cannon that they are roommates.
Chelsea: Oh my god, they were roommate.
Codey: Oh my god, they were roommates.
Codey: Wink, wink.
Chelsea: Oh my god.
Codey: Yeah.
Chelsea: Okay, yeah, just because I know you, I gotta play this game.
Chelsea: I was gonna say the most accurate game for bees is obviously be with guns.
Codey: Yeah.
Codey: Oh yeah, so that's, so Chelsea brought up this game uh, to us on the team chat, team slack.
Codey: Uh, and we were like, well, we got to play it.
Chelsea: bought it.
Codey: So we're gonna, so in the future, there will be an episode or a greenhouse or whatever, on the game called be with gun.
Chelsea: I cannot wait.
Codey: It's only it's only $5, so...
Chelsea: I bought it and.
Chelsea: Yeah, no, I because I was looking at beast simulator.
Chelsea: Gwen was like, what's that?
Chelsea: B with gun?
Chelsea: Can we watch a trailer?
Chelsea: And then he, it just shows us it'll be like it's angry and it just whips his gun out.
Chelsea: It's like now it's your turn to fight back.
Chelsea: I'm like, okay, sold.
Codey: Yep.
Chelsea: Sold.
Chelsea: So stay tuned for that episode.
Codey: Yep.
Codey: Thank you, Chelsea V Burton, for joining me for this episode.
Codey: Do you have anything that you would like to share with the audience?
Chelsea: Um, if you want to follow me on Instagram, my username is Zelda Greensley, I believe, I think.
Chelsea: If that's helpful, or Zelda Green.
Codey: Mm-hmm.
Chelsea: Um, I mostly just post.
Chelsea: Nothing, but, um, I'm looking into getting back into my music stuff, hosting concert videos, video game stuff, um, because I am a huge nerd, and I like Pokemon and Zelda.
Codey: Hmm.
Codey: Woo!
Chelsea: So if you want to see some of that stuff.
Chelsea: Remember they're welcome to join me there.
Codey: Are you looking for friends on neopets?
Chelsea: Yes, um, okay.
Codey: You gotta you gotta plug that.
Chelsea: Zelda Greensley.
Chelsea: So, yeah, please add me and I will give you stuff.
Codey: Yeah, I should probably, I'll, I'll do the premium and then I'll, I'll add, add you and you can give me stuff.
Chelsea: That sounds. Yes, join me and I will give you some.
Chelsea: Yeah, I'll give you stuff.
Codey: I wonder, like, is there a, is there a thing that it's like, who referred you to premium or?
Chelsea: No, I don't think so.
Chelsea: I'll look into it, but I never saw any sort of referral.
Codey: Because maybe like we could be friends and then maybe like if you would be like, suggest to this person that they get whatever and then you could get kickbacks from that.
Chelsea: Oh, I'll look into that.
Codey: I wonder, they probably actually don't have that because then people would just make a 1000000 um, accounts and then, like give themselves all the kickbacks, but...
Chelsea: Well, that's true.
Chelsea: Why can't we have anything nice?
Codey: Um, Because everyone, because the scalpers ruin it.
Chelsea: Can't have anything nice in this world.
Codey: Um, Uh, I, I mean, I don't have much to share the audience.
Chelsea: Oh.
Codey: I've just been yapping to you for a long time.
Codey: I guess the one thing to share is if you made it to this part of the podcast and you are someone that works in a museum or for bug insect biodiversity or conservation and you are looking for someone to hire.
Codey: Hit me up because I I currently have some uh, like part-time identification gigs, but other than that, it is not a fun time to be working in conservation in my country.
Chelsea: You gotta plug your LinkedIn.
Chelsea: Got to plug your LinkedIn at the bottom.
Codey: Dude, my LinkedIn, so I do have LinkedIn.
Codey: I mean it's just my name.
Codey: Um, and I docks myself everywhere.
Codey: My name's everywhere, but like, the link, I'm grumpy with LinkedIn.
Codey: It is such a scam.
Codey: But, I mean, sure, look, look me up on LinkedIn, if you're interested, um, or just reach out to me, uh, through LinkedIn or through the whatever.
Chelsea: It is.
Codey: Find me somewhere.
Codey: You can.
Codey: Blue Sky.
Codey: Um, What else has Blue Sky is the podcast.
Codey: So you can find the podcast at Tumblr and Blue Sky at THS Pod.
Chelsea: Mm.
Codey: You can also go to our website, harvestseason.club, to get feedbacks, links, the transcripts, all of this stuff that I've mentioned in this episode is going to be in there.
Codey: Also, while you're there, you can find a link to our Patreon, patreon.com slash GHS pod.
Codey: where you can support the show for as little as like 3 or 4 bucks a month.
Codey: Um, and in doing so, you get access to the Slack where we talk about things, cool things.
Codey: A lot of people have been posting some or responding to the bug month, which is great.
Codey: I love people's stuff.
Codey: One of the one of our friends who's on there, Stewart posted a picture of a book, like a dragonflies of Ireland book that they have.
Codey: And I was like, whoa, like, that is so cool.
Codey: Um, so it's just stuff like that.
Chelsea: Cool, yeah.
Codey: We also will post other things.
Codey: I'll post a photo of, uh, my one dog just got spayed and there's a really cute
Codey: I have some really cute photos of her with the cone of shame on.
Codey: Um, to so that she stops messing with her fricking incision.
Codey: Um, I'll post some of those. And I'll also post, uh, I'll post the bumblebee writing.
Codey: Um, I'm not, I'm gonna provide as little, like, no context.
Chelsea: Yes, that needs to be seen by as many people as possible.
Codey: I'm just gonna be like here it is.
Codey: Um, So yeah, that is everything.
Codey: Thank you, Chelsea, for joining me.
Chelsea: Thanks for having.
Codey: Thank you listeners for listening, and until next time, have a good harvest.
Chelsea: Have a good harvest.
Theme Tune: The harvest season is created by Al McKinley with support from our patrons, including our pro farmers, Kevin Stewart and Elisa.
Theme Tune: Our art is done by Mike the Brave, and our music is done by Nick Burgess.
Theme Tune: Feel free to visit our website, harvestseason.club for show notes and links to things we discussed in this episode.
Codey: Okay, well, that was a almost 3 hour rant.
Codey: Um, it's probably more like 2.5 hours after uh, Al cuts deadness.